<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doctrine of the kingdom and personal reign of Christ asserted and explained in an exposition upon Zach. 14, 5, 9 / by Ed. Bagshaw.</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B411</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5233</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13686596</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13686596</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101343</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29100)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101343)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 833:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doctrine of the kingdom and personal reign of Christ asserted and explained in an exposition upon Zach. 14, 5, 9 / by Ed. Bagshaw.</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Zechariah XIV, 5, 9 --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101343:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101343:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Doctrine OF THE KINGDOM And Perſonal Reign of CHRIST Aſſerted and Explained IN An Expoſition upon <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.5.9. By <hi>Ed. Bagſhaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:101343:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101343:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am not Ignorant, Chriſtian Reader, that the Doctrine of the <hi>Perſonal Reign of Chriſt, with his Saints upon Earth,</hi> (which thou wilt find aſſerted in the following Treatiſe) is commonly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained with very great prejudice; the Scriptures, which in plain terms affirm this, (and which I have indeavoured to reſtore unto their true meaning) being ordinarily interpreted in a ſenſe quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their literal import and ſignificancy: Which kind of expoſition (under the notion of being <hi>Miſterious</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi>) having held for many Ages, and been embraced, without any further enquiry, by men of the greateſt eminence for Holineſs and Learning, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe of the <hi>Reformed Religion;</hi> together with the Tragical Diſorders occaſioned in <hi>Germany,</hi> by ſuch, who in words aſſerted <hi>the Reign of Chriſt,</hi> but indeed, under that pretence, indeavoured to ſet up and eſtabliſh their own; this hath ever ſince made the True meaning of the Scripture Prophecies, in this matter, to be ſuſpected either of <hi>Novelty,</hi> or elſe of ſome Deſign to ſubvert all <hi>civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> which men, out of their impatience of ſubjection being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally apt to throw off, they may be ſuppoſed much more eaſily ready to be incited to it, if they ſhall be brought to think that they do here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>God, and his Chriſt, good ſervice,</hi> in attempting to ſet up his <hi>Kingdom, exalting themſelves, as the Robbers</hi> in the Jewiſh Nation did <hi>(Dan. 11.14.) to eſtabliſh the Viſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to all theſe exceptions and prejudices which it is not ſtrange that the truth is attended and received with, no more then
<pb facs="tcp:101343:3"/> that the Sun doth ordinarily ariſe in a cloud, I have this to ſay brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that neither <hi>Preſcription of time, nor authority of Perſons</hi> nor the <hi>Error of unſtable Men,</hi> ſhould ſo far prepoſſeſs and fill our minds, as to make us ſhut them up againſt the impreſſion and entrance of <hi>Divine truth,</hi> which, like the <hi>Light,</hi> ſhines ſometimes more, ſometimes leſs, according as it receives fainter, or more vigorous influences from the Spirit of God, its Fountain; and it can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at laſt, but a reſolved and peremptory <hi>Love of Darkneſs.</hi> which will deny it admittan e, by what imperfect <hi>Medium</hi> ſoever it be conveighed: The firſt inquiry therefore, by perſons ſincerely deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of true knowledge, ſhould be to learn whether this ſtate of things (which <hi>I</hi> have undertaken from the Scriptures to demonſtrate) be indeed Revealed by God or not, for then his words in this as well as in other Miſteries, muſt be received according to their plaineſt ſenſe, in ſpight both of our own, and others, pretendedly rational, Contradictions. And whoever are impartial and Unbiaſſed in this enquiry, reading the Scriptures in their own Light and evidence, and not viewing them thorough the falſe Perſpectives, which cuſtomary expoſitions have made for them, <hi>I</hi> believe they will be forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that they are not capable of any other Interpretation, but what the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Godly Jews;</hi> before; the Diſciples, in, and the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> for above <hi>300</hi> years, after our Saviours time, did underſtand them in: What that is I have here faithfully and plainly delivered, and as to myſelf, <hi>I</hi> can ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>I belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved therefore I ſpake,</hi> ſo as to others, I thought the truth to be of that importance, and withal the time of its accompliſhment ſo near that <hi>I</hi> was eaſily prevailed with, by Publiſhing this ſmall Treatiſe, to do my duty in ſtirring up others to a more ſevere and ſtrict examining and ſtudy of the Scriptures, then commonly they are accuſtomed to: I have no more to add, but to recommend it to the bleſſing of God, who can make ſhall and contemptible means, inſtrumental for the effecting of the greateſt Works.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>6th. <hi>M. 6, 1669.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101343:3"/>
            <head>THE Doctrine of the Kingdom, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Zech. 14. v. 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the Lord my God ſhall come, and all the Saints with thee: <hi>or, as it is in the Greek,</hi> with him. <hi>v. 9.</hi> And the Lord ſhall be King over all the earth; in that day the Lord ſhall be One, and his Name One.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the beginning of this Chapter, there is a Prophecy that <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> after it is Rebuilt, and the People of the Jews reſtored to it (as is promiſed, c. 1. 16. and c. 8. 3, 4, 5.) ſhall by their enemies be beſieged and taken (<hi>v.</hi> 1.) Preſently after which Deſolation, the Lord himſelf will come down from Heaven, and deſtroy <hi>thoſe Nations</hi> (v. 3. and 5.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jehovah,</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> whoſe <hi>coming</hi> is here ſpoken of, is no other then the <hi>Lord Chriſt,</hi> or, <hi>God Man,</hi> the ſecond Perſon in the Godhead; who is called <hi>The Branch</hi> (c. 6. 12. 13.) ſo named, either becauſe he ſprung from the <hi>ſtock of Jeſſe,</hi> as a Branch doth from the Root of a Tree (which is intimated) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.1.10. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.5.) and ſo uſed by our Saviour (<hi>Rev.</hi> 22 16.) or elſe the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (here tranſlated <hi>Branch</hi>) may be rendred, as it is by the Greek Interpreters, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> i. e. <hi>Morning riſe,</hi> or <hi>Day-ſpring,</hi> which very word is uſed by <hi>Zechary,</hi> in his Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Song, concerning our Saviour (<hi>Luke</hi> 1.78) with alluſion to which Phraſe, the Apoſtle ſaith, (<hi>Heb.</hi> 7.14.) It is <hi>manifeſt our Lord ſprang</hi> Greek <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) i. e. <hi>Aroſe as light out of Judah.</hi> To <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in both theſe capacities (for he is not only <hi>The Branch of Righteouſneſs) (Jer.</hi> 33.15.) but alſo <hi>The Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> as he is ſtiled (<hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2.) There is <hi>a Throne and ſupreme Dominion</hi> promiſed, both in that 6th. of <hi>Zechary,</hi> and more expreſsly (in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13 14.) Where he is called <hi>The Son of Man,</hi> which Name (as I think principally with reference to that Prophecy of <hi>Daniel</hi>) was by our Saviour, all the while he conveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon Earth, moſt commonly uſed: And that we might not doubt but is the ſame Perſon, who <hi>ſuffered</hi> then, that is ſpoken of <hi>to come</hi> and <hi>to Reign</hi> here, mention is made <hi>v.</hi> 4.) of his deſcent upon <hi>Mount Olivet;</hi> which was a place, where our Saviour, whilſt he was upon earth did
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101343:4"/> much converſe: <hi>Upon the Mount of Olives,</hi> He <hi>ſate</hi> when he foretold the <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and his own <hi>coming</hi> which was to follow, after the <hi>Diſperſion of the Jews,</hi> was fully accompliſhed (<hi>Mark</hi> 13.3.) Upon this <hi>Mount</hi> he began his <hi>ſufferings;</hi> feeling here that <hi>Anguiſh</hi> and <hi>Grief of Spirit,</hi> which made him ſweat drops of blood (<hi>Luke</hi> 22.39.) From hence, <hi>he aſcended up to Heaven, (Acts</hi> 1.9.12.) and hither ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Angels promiſe, is he to <hi>come down in the ſame manner (v.</hi> 11.) The fulfilling of which Promiſe, and the Glory which ſhall follow upon it, is in this place of <hi>Zechary</hi> prophecyed of.</p>
            <p>Two obſervations are clear in the words.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That the Lord Chriſt, will come in Perſon, and take to himſelf the Monarchy, or, Soveraign Dominion over the whole earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That when the Lord Chriſt comes to reign upon Earth, all his Saints ſhall come with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1.</note>The firſt Obſervation is, <hi>That the Lord Chriſt ſhall come in Perſon, and take to himſelf the Monarchy, or Soveraign Dominion over the whole Earth.</hi> This <hi>coming of Chriſt,</hi> which is <hi>His coming to Reign upon Earth,</hi> however it is now decryed, and ſpoken againſt by many, yet (as I ſhall anon prove) it was the firm and conſtant belief, of almoſt all the Primitive Church, for above three hundred years together after our Saviours time; and it is evidently prophecied of, not only in this, but in ſeveral other Scriptures: As</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 9.6.7. <hi>opened.</hi>
               </note>1. <hi>Iſay.</hi> 9.6.7. <hi>The Son,</hi> who is there ſaid to be <hi>given to us,</hi> i. e. to the <hi>Jews, The Government</hi> likewiſe is ſaid to be laid <hi>upon his Shoulder,</hi> of which <hi>Government</hi> there is to be <hi>no end,</hi> and the exerciſe thereof is to be, in a viſible way of Adminiſtration, <hi>upon the Throne of</hi> David <hi>to order and to eſtabliſh it:</hi> Which is in effect to ſay, that <hi>the Son</hi> there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied of, ſhall become a <hi>King,</hi> and rule his ſubjects in a viſible manner as <hi>David</hi> did: Unto which Prophecy, the Angel in expreſs words alludes (<hi>Luke</hi> 1.32.33.) And this was ſo underſtood, as I have explained it, by all thoſe who acknowledg Chriſt; to be the <hi>Son of</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid; or, <hi>The King of Iſrael,</hi> as our Saviour is called (<hi>John</hi> 1 49.) And that confeſſion of <hi>Nathaniel</hi> is owned by our Saviour to be an effect of his Faith (<hi>v.</hi> 50.) And when our Saviour went up to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that ſolemn acclamation ſignified no leſs, when the multitude cryed out, <hi>Bleſſed is the Kingdom, which cometh in the Name of the Lord (the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) of our Father</hi> David (<hi>Mark</hi> 11.10.) whereby they plainly inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, that they did then at that time expect (and the Evangeliſt <hi>Luke</hi> doth in expreſs words declare ſo much (<hi>Luke</hi> 19.11.) That the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi> (1. The Kingdom which God had promiſed to one of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101343:4"/> Poſterity of <hi>David) ſhould appear,</hi> or <hi>be made manifeſt</hi> i. be then ſet up and viſibly adminiſtred in its Glory: which, though, as to the time, it was not ſo ſuddenly to be eſtabliſhed as they expected; yet, as to the thing it ſelf, they were not at all miſtaken, for our Saviour doth there intimate, that he would <hi>come again in perſon, and deſtroy his enemies, (Luke</hi> 19, 27.) Which is the firſt preparatory work, to the ſetting up of his <hi>Kingdom:</hi> and afterwards the Evangeliſt <hi>John,</hi> doth in a viſion ſee the actual completion of this, when upon the <hi>ſounding of the ſeventh Trumpet,</hi> he heard <hi>loud voices in Heaven, ſaying, the Kingdoms of the World are become the Kingdomes of the Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall Reign for ever and ever (Rev.</hi> 11.15.) which place comparing it with <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. ſhowes, that this was nothing elſe, but a finiſhing of that <hi>Miſtery of God,</hi> which in all the Proceeding Ages, <hi>he had declared by his Servants the Prophets:</hi> Hence it is, that, after his victorious and final ſubduing of his Enemies, <hi>John</hi> ſees the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> attired with <hi>a Tryumphant Robe,</hi> and upon it this Regal Inſcription <hi>King of Kings and Lord of Lords (Rev.</hi> 19.16.) which is the name that was given to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> the Head of the <hi>Firſt Monarchy (Dan.</hi> 2.37.) and is afterwards upon a much better Title, given to <hi>Chriſt</hi> when he hath actually made himſelf the <hi>viſible Head</hi> of the <hi>Fifth and laſt,</hi> for which reaſon, it is called a <hi>New Name, (Rev.</hi> 3.12.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another place, wherein the <hi>Viſible and Perſonal Reign of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 11.</note> is prophecied of, is <hi>Iſay</hi> 11. from <hi>v</hi> 1. <hi>to v.</hi> 10. Where <hi>Chriſt</hi> is called <hi>a Rod out of the ſtemm of Jeſſe,</hi> and of him it is ſaid, that, <hi>he ſhould bear Rule over the Nations unto whom they ſhould ſeek,</hi> or, <hi>ſubmit themſelves</hi> (according to that in (<hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10.) <hi>Unto him ſhall the obedience of the Nations be</hi>) The Graces, wherewith he ſhould be indued for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are mentioned (<hi>v.</hi> 2.3.) together with his actual Ruling, <hi>Judging,</hi> and Governing according to them (<hi>v.</hi> 4.) <hi>where to ſmite the earth with the Sword of his Mouth,</hi> is not (as it is commonly underſtood) barely to <hi>convince</hi> the World by <hi>Preaching,</hi> but to <hi>conquer</hi> it by <hi>Power,</hi> as it is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly expreſſed (<hi>Rev.</hi> 19 13 14, 15. Which likewiſe is principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, intended in that excellent Song (<hi>Pſ.</hi> 45.3.4.5) <hi>The Riding, Gird<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Sword, conquering and ſubduing of enemies,</hi> there ſpoken of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only the Preparatory work unto the ſetting up of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt; whereupon it follows v</hi> 6.) <hi>Thy Throne, O God, is for ever and ever the Scepter of thy Kingdom is a Right Scepter, or a Scepter of Equity.</hi> 1. Ruling in Righteouſneſs, which as it was ſpoken of Chriſt ſo it is by the Apoſtle applyed to him, (<hi>Heb.</hi> 1.8.9.) Suitable to who it is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101343:5"/> that Prophecy (<hi>Iſ.</hi> 2.4.) <hi>He ſhall judge among the Nations, and ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke many people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Prophecy concerning the <hi>reign of Chriſt,</hi> is Iſa. 35:4.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.4. <hi>opened.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Behold your God ſhall come with vengeance; God with a recompence</hi> (i. e. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſing that miſchief which the enemies did his people, by return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame upon them themſelves, as si threatned (<hi>Joel</hi> 3.4.) <hi>and he will ſave you by coming</hi> there, that a viſible Appearance of the Lord himſelf in Perſon, is meant, appears from (<hi>v.</hi> 2.) where it is ſaid, <hi>Carmel and Sharon</hi> (i. e. All the places of <hi>Judea,</hi> which of old were famous but at that time ſhall be enriched with an extraordinary fruitfulneſs; as follows in this chapter of <hi>Zachary. (v.</hi> 10 11.) compared with <hi>Iſ.</hi> 51.3. and (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.35.36.) <hi>They ſhall ſee the Glory of the Lord</hi> i. the <hi>Lord Chriſt;</hi> who is ſo ſtiled (<hi>Iſ.</hi> 40.5.) and whom to <hi>ſee</hi> in his <hi>Beauty</hi> (i. e. when he <hi>appears the ſecond time,</hi> in the luſtre of his Majeſty, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin,</hi> i. without the imputation of ſin, which before did cloud and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe his Beauty, to ſee him then) it is reckoned as the ſum and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect on of that happineſs, which is promiſed unto thoſe <hi>who walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly (Iſay</hi> 33.17.) Whereupon <hi>Sion</hi> is earneſtly called upon <hi>to behold her God, (Iſa.</hi> 40 9.10 11.) For as the Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> (according as is there prophecied) came once to ſave his people, by caring and <hi>laying down his life for them,</hi> as a ſhepherd; ſo ſhall he hereafter come again, and that in the ſame nature, to rule them as a <hi>Prince,</hi> and to deliver them from their enemies. And then in the Prophets words, <hi>how beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful ſhall be the Feet of</hi> thoſe, that can bring ſuch <hi>tidings</hi> to <hi>Sion,</hi> as to ſay unto her, <hi>Thy God Reigneth,</hi> Then ſhall the <hi>Watchmen lift up the voice and ſing,</hi> for joy of ſo glorious a ſpectacle, for this ſhall not be an obſcure and hidden thing, but <hi>eye ſhall ſee to eye when God brings back</hi> Sion (<hi>Iſay</hi> 52.7, 8.) That Phraſe of ſeeing <hi>Eye to Eye,</hi> is very remarkable; it being uſed but once before, and that (in <hi>Numb.</hi> 14 14) concerning Gods manifeſting of his <hi>glory</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in a <hi>cloud and fire,</hi> that reſted upon the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and the beholding of this, is called a <hi>ſeeing of God Eye to Eye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> (for ſo it ſhould be rendred and not <hi>Face to Face</hi>) i. plainly, without any thing interpoſed to hinder the Viſion. But theſe beamings forth of Divine glory, ſhall be much more conſpicuous and diſcernible hereafter in the humane Nature of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and equally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the view of beholders. For the very ſame perſon, whom in the days of his <hi>Humilation,</hi> and Abaſement, in bearing the ſins of Mankind, <hi>Men did abhorr,</hi> him hereafter <hi>Kings ſhall ſee, and ariſe</hi> (in token of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence) <hi>and worſhip</hi> (Iſa. 49.7.] And as <hi>many</hi> formerly <hi>were aſtonied at
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101343:5"/> his Viſage,</hi> ſo then, in ſign of their Awe and ſubmiſſion, <hi>They ſhall ſhut their Mouths at him (Iſay</hi> 52.13, 14, 15.) Of which reverence and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, to be paid by all, unto the Soveraignty of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when he comes <hi>to Reign,</hi> the Pſalmiſt likewiſe prophecies, (<hi>Pſ.</hi> 72.15.17.)</p>
            <p n="4">4. This is gathered alſo, from <hi>Iſay</hi> 62 11.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 62.11. <hi>ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
               </note> Where God calleth upon his Miniſters from the vtmoſt ends of the Earth, to proclaim unto <hi>Sion, Behold, thy ſalvation</hi> (or rather thy <hi>Saviour,</hi> or <hi>thy Jeſus) cometh, behold his reward is with him:</hi> which laſt words are uſed by our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when he foretells the ſuddenneſs of his <hi>ſecond coming (Rev.</hi> 22.12.) Which though it be indeed to deſtroy his Enemies,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> yet the principal end is to ſave and to deliver his people, by reigning with, and among them: Of which time <hi>Obadiah</hi> ſpeaks (<hi>v.</hi> 21.) <hi>Saviours</hi> (i. the ſupream and moſt excellent Saviour, who is alſo called <hi>Wiſdoms, (Prov.</hi> 9.1) as being <hi>moſt wiſe) ſhall come upon Mount Sion, to judge the Mount of Eſau,</hi> (i. e. To puniſh all the enemies of his People, who, with reference to the enmity of <hi>Eſau</hi> againſt <hi>Jacob,</hi> are frequently called <hi>Edomites</hi> (as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34, 5, 6, 8, and 63.1, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and (i. after that Judgement execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon thoſe Enemies) <hi>the Kingdom</hi> (i. the ſupream Dominion and Soveraignty, of which <hi>Obadiah</hi> here prophecies) <hi>ſhall be the Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly. All thoſe places, wherein mention is made of Gods raiſing up <hi>David,</hi> in the <hi>latter days;</hi> to be <hi>King</hi> among and over his people, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be meant of any elſe, then of the Lord <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who, according to the Fleſh, was of the poſterity and race of <hi>David;</hi> and who in order to the <hi>fulfilling</hi> of all thoſe <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and for the ſolace of his faithful ſubjects, as well as terror of his Enemies; muſt hereafter Reign in as Viſible and apparent a manner, as ever <hi>David</hi> did: Thus God by <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel,</hi> ſpeaks expreſly, <hi>I will ſave my flock, and I will ſet up one Shepherd, over them, and he ſhall ſeed them, even my Servant</hi> David, <hi>he ſhall feed them, and he ſhall be their Shepherd, and</hi> I <hi>the Lord will be their God, and my ſervant</hi> David, <hi>a prince among them,</hi> Ezek. 34.23, 24.) ſo cap. 37.24.25. <hi>David my Servant ſhall be King over them, and they ſhall all have one Shepherd, and they ſhall dwell in the Land that I have given unto Jacob, and my Servant David, ſhall be their Prince for ever.</hi> Of him, and his perſonal Reign upon Earth, it is that God ſpeaks by <hi>Jeremy, I will raiſe, up unto David a righ eous Branch, and a King ſhall reign</hi> (i. e.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> He as a <hi>King</hi> ſhall <hi>reign</hi>) and <hi>ſhall proſper</hi> (or, <hi>ſhall deal wiſely,</hi> as the Word is Tranſlated, in a Prophecy of the ſame Perſon, and to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe (<hi>Iſay</hi> 52.13.) <hi>And ſhall execute Judgement and righteouſneſs in the Earth, in his days Judah ſhall he ſaved, and Iſrael ſhall dwell ſafely, and this is his Name, whereby they ſhall call him Jehovah our righteouſneſs.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101343:6"/> (Jer. 23.4.5, 6.) And then as he ſpeaks in another place, <hi>they ſhall ſerve the Lord their God, and David their King, (Jer.</hi> 30 9.) Of which time alſo the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſpeaks in that excellent and clear Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy (<hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.4, 5) All which places, are ſo full and plain for the Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Reſidence and Reign of our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> upon Earth, that without great violence and wreſtling they cannot poſſibly be otherwiſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</p>
            <p>That all theſe Prophecies of Scripture, with many more of the ſame Nature and Tendency, muſt be literally interpreted, as really and plainly meaning the things they ſpeak of, beſides the evidence of the words themſelves, which have nothing in them of Darkneſs or Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, there are theſe reaſons which may ſerve farther to evince it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 1.</note>Firſt, Becauſe God is very exact and careful in the fulfilling of his Promiſes, for this end they were written, that they might be ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting records of Gods goodneſs, which his people might always plead in Prayer with him, and wait in Hope for their full accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (<hi>Jer.</hi> 30 2, 3.) And for this end we are commanded to read them, becauſe <hi>none of thoſe things ſhall ſail</hi> of being effectually perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which are prophecied of, (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 34.16. And our Saviour hath given ſuch a Teſtimony to this purpoſe, as nothing can be more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs. <hi>Heaven and Earth,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhall paſs away, before one jot or title of the Law. (i,</hi> Of the writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> whether we conſider their precepts, or their Predictions) <hi>ſhall fail, till all things be done (i.</hi> Till every thing be exactly fulfilled which they have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) for Gods <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs (which he magnifies above all his Name,</hi> as the moſt glorious of his attributes <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138 2.) doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage him to the performance of the leaſt and moſt minate circumſtance, which can from his word be rightly gathered as a diſcovery of his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture intentions: but if all their places, with many more that may be quoted, concerning the <hi>Perſonal Reign of Chriſt upon earth,</hi> before the laſt and Univerſal Judgement, may be eluded by <hi>Miſtical Interpretations</hi> a very great and conſiderate portion of Scripture Prophecy, will be utterly loſt and made uſeleſs; nay ſeem to be written to no other purpoſe, but to beget in true Believers vain hopes, which far be it from any ſo much as to imagine, ſince God, as he doth not <hi>Tempt, (James</hi> 1.14.15.) ſo neither will he <hi>Deceive</hi> any, but rather ruine this admirble frame of the Univerſe, then not employ his whole power to effect, and that to the uttermoſt, what ever any of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, in his Name and by his Spirit have foretold.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101343:6"/>
            <p>Secondly, Another Reaſon may be taken from the litteral, fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 2.</note> already of other Prophecies; which were much difficult in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing, and ſome of them not tending ſo viſibly to illuſtrate the glory of God and of his Chriſt, as this I am now inſiſting upon: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theſe I ſhall mention only two, which, in their ſeveral kinds are truly admirable.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Concerning the <hi>Birth and ſufferings of Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Concerning the <hi>Riſe and Reign of Anti-Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt remarkable Prophecy which hath been literally fulfilled, is that concerning <hi>the Birth and ſufferings of Chriſt:</hi> that <hi>the eternal So of God</hi> ſhould become <hi>a mortal Man;</hi> that <hi>He who made the World</hi> ſhould ſubject himſelf to the penury and want of a Calamitous life, and after that, ſo far <hi>empty himſelf</hi> of his Native glory,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note> as to <hi>dye an accurſed death;</hi> this contains in it ſo many wonders, that before it was done, the Prophet complains very few did <hi>believe the report of it;</hi> and yet not a ſyllable which concerned our Saviours <hi>Humiliation</hi> and <hi>inglorious eſtate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ.</hi> 53.1.</note> as <hi>Man,</hi> but was by him fully accompliſhed; for which exactneſs and care there is the reaſon given, both by our Saviour and the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt. <hi>All theſe things were done that the Scriptures of the Prophets might be fulfilled (Mat.</hi> 29.54.56.) And it is very obſervable, that when our Saviour was nailed to the Croſs, being then even in the Agony and pangs of Death, yet that nothing might be omitted, which with the leaſt poſſibility or plea could be urged as a part of his ſufferings; and calling then to mind that he had not yet drank the <hi>Vinegar and Gall,</hi> which the Pſalmiſt mentions (<hi>Pſal</hi> 69.21.) He preſently cryed out, <hi>I thirſt;</hi> and having received that bitter potion from one of the ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, he ſaid, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>It is finiſhed, i.</hi> All things which the Scriptures have foretold concerning, not only my Death, but all the manner and circumſtances of my dying, they are now to a Title accompliſhed; and then in token of thankfulneſs, that his <hi>Father</hi> had heard and ſtrengthned him hitherto, for this difficult, and ſeeming leſs noble,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 19.28.30. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7</note> part of his work, <hi>He bowed his head,</hi> and contentedly <hi>gave up the Ghoſt,</hi> from which exactneſs it is eaſie to gather, that the ſame truth and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which our Lord manifeſted in coming into, and going out of the World, he doth intend to ſhow by haſtening this return, and in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral fulfilling of thoſe promiſes, which concern his <hi>Kingdome</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation:</hi> and for any to read them by a limited and reſtrained ſenſe, it is neither to deale faithfully with the Scripture (of which <hi>every Jota and Title muſt be fulfilled</hi>) nor honorably with our Lord <hi>Chriſt;</hi> who certainly hath merited ſo much by the punctualneſs, as well as the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101343:7"/> greatneſs of his ſufferings, that his inheritance of <hi>ruling all Nations,</hi> ſhould not be abridged or curtailed: ſince he did not, when he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, mince the matter, nor eaſe himſelf by a diſtinction, but did <hi>Totum ſeſum exsipere, Take the whole Chap,</hi> without ſhedding a drop, or aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the rigour of the ſmalleſt circumſtance, which did but ſeem to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon him, why ſhould we then imagine but thoſe many promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, concerning his actual Reign and ſoveraignty over the world, will be made good in the moſt clear and comprehenſive Latitude of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture language: eſpecially ſince beſide the truth and faithfulneſs of God which doth engage him to perform it, this laſt doth in a more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent and ſignal manner advance the honour of our Saviour then the former; which <hi>the Father who loves the Son, and hath given all th ngs into his hands,</hi> will not at his requeſt deny him. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.8.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Prophecy, the fulfiling of which is an Argument that <hi>Chriſt</hi> will come and <hi>reign upon earth,</hi> in the ſame viſible manner as is prophecied of him, is that concerning the <hi>riſe and reign of Anti-Chriſt,</hi> that <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> which is ſo directly contrary to mens natural ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, and likewiſe met with ſuch fierce oppoſiition from enraged and cruel men, ſhould notwithſtanding all this prevaile over the world, had in it Miracle and ſtrangeneſs enough; but, after this Religion was planted, and almoſt an univerſal obedience was paid unto it, that a company of <hi>Impoſtors</hi> (as they are called,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 2 <hi>John</hi> v 7.) ſhould riſe up and make uſe of this very Religion, to deſtroy it's ſelf, and wreſt it's Doctrine quite contrary to it's true intent and meaning, that any ſhould be ſo impiouſly daring, as to perſwade the world (which <hi>Chriſt</hi> came to <hi>enlighten, John</hi> 12.35.36. that to be <hi>Ignorant</hi> and <hi>Blind, i. e.</hi> To be willing to be deceived and ſeduced, was the next way to be <hi>Chriſts Diſciples,</hi> and that they were moſt likely to ſerve God and to obey his commands beſt, who ſtudyed his word leaſt; this is too prodigious and amazing an Impiety, that one might have ſaid of it in former ages, what the Apoſtle ſpeaks concerning the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>It could never enter into the heart of man to conceive it,</hi> but yet ſuch groſs deluſions were exactly foretold (2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.1.10. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.2.3.4. 2 <hi>Pet,</hi> 2. <hi>Revel.</hi> 13. And we have lived to ſee them, in their moſt amazing and ſtupendious particulars, literally accompliſhed, ſince then, that <hi>Doctrine</hi> is taught concerning the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding of Marriage,</hi> and <hi>the abſtaining from Meats,</hi> which the Spirit of God hath already called the <hi>Doctrine of Divils:</hi> ſince there is a <hi>lawleſs man</hi> who now actually <hi>ſits in the Temple (or Church of God)</hi> challenging to himſelf Divine power and honour: ſince that Beaſt <hi>who kills all that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101343:7"/> will not worſhip his Image, and receive his mark, (i. e.</hi> Who will not teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their Communion with him, by ſome viſible and outward Act of Conformity,) is not only <hi>Raſen</hi> long ſince, but <hi>reigning in Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.</note> the <hi>Citty with ſeven Hills, which is adorned with Gold and pretious ſtones, and makes all the Nations of the World drunk with the wine of her Fornication, i. e.</hi> Which hath a ſpecious glittering, and Pompous Religion, whereby ſhe doth bewitch the Credulous World, and makes his poyſonous pills of <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Will-worſhip</hi> ſecurely ſwallowed. In a word, ſince <hi>Anti-Chriſt</hi> is come, in his full proportion; and according to thoſe Lineaments wherein he was before deceived? why then ſhould we doubt, but our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> will alſo come to <hi>Reign,</hi> in the very ſame manner as is prophecied concerning him, can we think that God will be more exact in fulfiling the Prophecies, which concern the advancement of his Enemy, then in accompliſhing thoſe which make for the <hi>Ezalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of his Son? ſhall the <hi>Kingdome of Anti-Chriſt</hi> for thus many hundred of Years, be an univerſal extent, that the Scriptures about him might be fulfiled; and ſhall not <hi>the kingdome of Chriſt,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the accompliſhment of the ſame Scriptures, be much more large and comprehenſive? I cannot ſee the leaſt pretence of ſolid Reaſon, why we ſhould ſo much as once doubt of it; for the ſame <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Anti-Chriſt ſhould come,</hi> hath foretold likewiſe, that <hi>he ſhould be deſtroyed;</hi> whom <hi>Chriſt ſhall aboliſh by the brightneſs of his appearance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>John</hi> 7.</note> i. e. <hi>by the ſetting up of his kingdome</hi> (as they are joyned 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.1.) And in the ruine of that great <hi>Impoſtour,</hi> erect unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon Earth a durable Throne of Glory, then will he put an end to all thoſe <hi>Cheats</hi> and <hi>Diveliſh Deluſions,</hi> whereby the face of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity hath hitherto been disfi ured, and according as <hi>Zechary</hi> here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, make <hi>the Name of the Lord, [i. e.</hi> his Worſhip] <hi>one as the Lord</hi> himſelf <hi>is</hi> [in his Nature] <hi>One</hi> which happineſs in this degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and forlorn poſture of things, we cannot hope for untill that <hi>kingdome come,</hi> which we (for the moſt part ignorantly) but daily pray for; and our <hi>Lord from Heaven,</hi> be put in full poſſeſſion upon Earth of his promiſed and dearely purchaſed Inheritance:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2.3.</note> in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation and foreſight of which he couragiouſly bore <hi>the contradiction of ſinners againſt himſelf, induring the Croſs, deſpiſeing the ſhame, and is now ſate down at the right hand of the throne of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.13.</note> and as the ſame Authour ſaith in another place <hi>exſpect,</hi> or, <hi>watch</hi> till the time cometh, <hi>that his Enemies be made the footſtool of his feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Our Saviour himſelf never denyed,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon third.</note> that he both was and would be a <hi>King</hi> in that glorious and viſible manner, which is prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101343:8"/> of — for though, while he was upon Earth, the Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> acted in a way ſuitable to that <hi>form of a ſervant,</hi> which he then took upon him (and therefore his <hi>kingdome and patience</hi> are joyned together, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.9) Yet when he was urged by the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> he told them that he was <hi>the Son of God,</hi> and that they ſhould ſee him <hi>ſitting on the right hand of power (Mat.</hi> 26.64.) And before <hi>Pilate</hi> he confeſſed he was a <hi>King,</hi> which he calls <hi>a witneſſing to the Truth [John</hi> 18.37.] and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiles it <hi>a good confeſſion</hi> [1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.13.14.] and though our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our then ſaid to <hi>Pilate,</hi> that, <hi>his kingdome was not of this world,</hi> ſo as to be advanced by worldly acts, and to be ſet up by the <hi>fighting of his followers, [v</hi> 36.] Yet he did not deny that he was to have <hi>a viſible kingdome in the world;</hi> but on the contrary doth clearly intiemate it, both there, and in ſeveral other places: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. When <hi>Peter</hi> in the name of the reſt of the Diſciples, doth ask our Saviour what <hi>reward</hi> they ſhould have for <hi>leaving all, and following him,</hi> our Saviour replyes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 19 28. <hi>opened</hi>
               </note> that, beſides <hi>an hundred fold recompence in this life,</hi> given as an <hi>earneſt</hi> of ſomthing better, they ſhould be fully recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>in the regeneration i. e.</hi> As the <hi>Syriacke</hi> tranſlates it, <hi>in the new world,</hi> or,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>in the world to come,</hi> as it is called [<hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5.] This is <hi>the new Heaven, and new Earth,</hi> which <hi>Iſay</hi> prophecies of [<hi>Iſa</hi> 65.17.] and <hi>which</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, we exſpect according to his promiſe</hi> [2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13.] and is the ſame time, with that of the ſounding of the <hi>ſeventh Trumpet [Rev.</hi> 11] for then <hi>the kingdomes of this world, are to become the kingdomes of the Lord and of his Chriſt,</hi> [v. 15.] and then <hi>he will give a reward unto his ſervants the Prophets, and to his Saints,</hi> and to them <hi>that fear him both ſmall and great</hi> [v. 18.] this is called (<hi>Acts.</hi> 3.) <hi>The times of refreſhing,</hi> (v, 19.) and <hi>the time of reſtitution of all things</hi> (v. 21.) <hi>i.</hi> That time wherein the ſtate of the World ſhall be renewed and altered, and that perfection and beauty put upon it, wherewith it was endued at the firſt Creation, as is evidently prophecied (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.6.7.8.9. and 51.3. add 65.25. with <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 36.34.35.) And this is the time in which our Saviour promiſeth; that all his followers ſhall have a rich and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple requital for all their temporal hardſhip and loſſes; which time is not the <hi>final judgement</hi> (for none of the forementioned places do ſpeak of that) but the time of our Saviours <hi>Reign</hi> in which he ſaith that his Diſciples ſhall ſhare with him, both there and again (<hi>Luke</hi> 22.29 30. and not only they unto whom that anſwer was made, but <hi>all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.11.12.) and <hi>all who overcome</hi> i. e. <hi>who have the words of Chriſt, and hold them faſt unto the end,</hi> even <hi>they</hi> have a promiſe of the ſame royalty, which the Lord Chriſt hath received from his Father, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101343:8"/> that is <hi>To have power over the Nations, and to rule them with a rod of Iron,</hi> [Rev. 2.26.27] Which is celebrated in that Tryumphant Song of the Church, <hi>thou haſt made us unto our God, Kings and Pri ſts, and we ſhall reign upon earth,</hi> [Rev. 5.10]</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our Saviour compares himſelf; upon his withdrawing from earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.12. <hi>ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
               </note> unto ſuch a Prince, who goes a far Journey, <hi>to receive a Kingdom,</hi> and then returns in perſon to mannage it (<hi>Luke</hi> 19 12.) Which compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is very obſervable, becauſe is was uſed and ſpoken by our Sav our, at ſuch a time, when his hearers thought that <hi>the Kingdom of God,</hi> (which from the Prophets they had received ſuch clear diſcoveries of) was juſt then upon the point of <hi>Appearing (v.</hi> 11.) And though by mentioning the delay that would be interpoſed, our Saviour doth check the impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and eager haſt of their deſires, yet doth he ſufficiently manifeſt, that, at the time appointed, he would come, and in perſon deſtroy all his Enemies (<hi>v</hi> 27) as we find he actually is ſeen to do (<hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11.21.) Which is the direct purport of all thoſe Prophecies that I have mentioned.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 1 6. <hi>opened.</hi>
               </note> who were now in a great meaſure enlightned [for by our Saviours <hi>breathing upon them, they had received the Holy Ghoſt</hi> [Joh. 20.22.] <hi>and their mind was opened to underſtand the Scriptures</hi> (Luke 24.45) Yet then they asked our Saviour, whether he <hi>would at that time reſto e the Kingdom unto Iſrael: (Acts</hi> 1.6) where, by <hi>Kingdom</hi> is meant that Dominion and Soveraignty promiſed to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> (in <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.29. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60, 10, 11, 12. <hi>Micah</hi> 4, 6, 7, 8.) At which time the Lord Chriſt himſelf ſhall be at the Head of his Returning Iſraelites; (Iſa. 52.12. c. 35.8. according to the Hebrews; Hoſ 1.11. Mic. 2.12, 13.) And our Saviour in his Anſwer, doth not rebuke them for expecting ſuch <hi>a Kingd m,</hi> (for the Scriptures which foretell it are clear, and muſt be fulfilled) but only he proves the curioſity, in that they required af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods <hi>Arcana,</hi> and deſired to know <hi>thoſe Times and Seaſons,</hi> (i. the particular time of ſetting up that promiſed Kingdom) which as yet were not revealed, but reſerved <hi>by the Father, in his own Power,</hi> It is for the ſame Reaſon, that the <hi>two Sons of Zebedee, (Mat.</hi> 20.22. are check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who did believe that <hi>Chriſt,</hi> was to be <hi>a King,</hi> nor are they blamed for that, but they diſcovered a prepoſterous ambition, in deſiring to be advanced above their Brethren, and utterly miſtook both the time and manner of ſetting up that <hi>Kingdom</hi> and therefore our Saviour (to take them off from their thought, which then poſſeſſed them, of preſent greatneſs) mentions his <hi>ſufferings,</hi> as the way whereby he (and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently all his Followers) were to enter into Glory. So <hi>Luke</hi> 24 20 21.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101343:9"/> When the <hi>two Dsſciples</hi> were diſconſolate for the death of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moaning themſelves as if now all their hopes were loſt, for <hi>we,</hi> ſay they, <hi>truſted that it had been he,</hi> who ſhould <hi>have redeemed Iſrael:</hi> 1. Who ſhould have aſſerted our Nation into that liberty and freedom, which the Prophets ſpeak of, as the effect of <hi>the Sons being given to them, (Iſ.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Jer,</hi> 30.8, 9, 10.) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Our Saviour, in his reply, doth grant their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, but reproves them ſharply, for not being better acquainted with the Scriptures, out of which they might have learn't. That <hi>Chriſt ought to have ſuffered all thoſe things, and then to enter into his Glory,</hi> where by <hi>his Glory,</hi> is meant <hi>his Kingdom,</hi> as is plain (<hi>Mark</hi> 10 37. compared with <hi>Mat.</hi> 20 21.) In the ſame manner, after his Reſurrection, our Saviour doth blame his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> in that forementioned demand of theirs, not for their expectation, but for their <hi>haſt,</hi> and therefore he bids them <hi>(v. .)</hi> prepare for <hi>ſuffering,</hi> and <hi>witneſſing,</hi> as their next immediate work, His Kingdom being to be prolonged, as to the ſetting of it up, till the number of his <hi>witneſſes</hi> was compleated (<hi>Rev.</hi> 6.11.) And then there ſhould be <hi>no longer time, (Rev.</hi> 10 6.) i. No more delay: but he would preſently come,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>to reward his Servants, and to deſtroy them which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the earth,</hi> (Rev. 11.15.18.)</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the <hi>Revelation,</hi> which our Saviour ſaith, (cap. 1.1.) That he had received <hi>from the Father</hi> to this end, <hi>that he might ſhow unto his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, what things were to come to paſs hereafter,</hi> there we have this <hi>Reign</hi> fully manifeſted and the time of it, duration for a Thouſand years, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly mentioned (<hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4.6.) So that now there can ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally be no more ſcruple about it, becauſe the words of that book are declared to be <hi>the true and faithful ſayings of God; [Rev.</hi> 19 9] and they are pronounced <hi>Bleſſed who read and hear the words of the Prophecy, and keep the things that are written therein,</hi> i. Who live up to a full belief, and expectation of them: But if ſuch a <hi>reign</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as is there ſpoken of, ſhall never be, <hi>how can thoſe ſayings be true?</hi> or, if they are to have another interpretation put upon them, then the words themſelves do naturally and neceſſarily import, <hi>how are they Faithful?</hi> So that I conclude this third reaſon with this, that our Saviour was ſo far from denying his <hi>perſonal reign</hi> and <hi>viſible Kingdom</hi> upon Earth, that he doth clearly own and aſſert it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">4th. Reaſ.</note>Fourthly. Another reaſon, why the Prophecies of Scripture, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>reign of Chriſt,</hi> are literally to be underſtood, is this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this way of putting myſtical and ſpiritual meanings, upon plain and poſitive texts, is very unſafe and dangerous; many Hereſies, were of old introduced, and ſtill are fomented by it, I believe it was upon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101343:9"/> this very prtence that ſome in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> did deny <hi>the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead,</hi> and others as <hi>Hymaeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetas</hi> did affirme,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15 12. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>it was paſt already,</hi> and indeed what truth can be ſo clearly revealed, which may not by taking the words in a figurative ſence, be altogether eluded! farre be it therefore from us, <hi>to limit the holy One of Iſrael,</hi> or to ſeek how we may <hi>darken his counſail by our words,</hi> (which if in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect they contradict his muſt needs be) <hi>without knowledge,</hi> ſince it hath pleaſed God to promiſe, that <hi>his Chriſt, ſhall reign with his Saints upon earth,</hi> let us not by unbeleif, [for I cannot yet ſee from what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther root ſuch denyal can proceed] caſt off the mercy: but rather la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to receive the <hi>truths of God,</hi> according to his own word, in the utmoſt extent, and moſt comprehenſive meaning of it, and not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what ſeems poſſible in our own narrow conceptions.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, This <hi>reign of Chriſt in perſon</hi> ſerves to make up and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat<note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 5.</note> the great <hi>Myſtery of the Goſpel;</hi> which conſiſts, not only in having <hi>God our Saviour,</hi> but the ſame God, in the ſame humane Nature, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>our King;</hi> and this was that <hi>Miſtery,</hi> which God revealed to the <hi>Prophets (Rev.</hi> 10.7.) and remained to be fulfiled under the <hi>ſeventh Trumpet</hi> (as I have already obſerved from <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.15.) therefore when our Saviour was taken up into Heaven, the Angels comforted his amazed and ſorrowful Diſciples with this, that, <hi>the ſame Jeſus ſhould return as he went</hi> (i. <hi>in the ſame viſible and apparent manner) as he went away (Acts</hi> 1.11.) which alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> teſtifies (<hi>c.</hi> 3.19. 20, 21.) <hi>when the times of refreſhing (i.</hi> the time of calling the <hi>Jews,</hi> which will be a time ſo glorious that it will be as <hi>life from the dead,</hi> (Rom. 11.15.) <hi>ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord; whom the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven muſt receive</hi> until that time, which he then calls <hi>the time of the recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of all things, which God hath ſpoken of by the mouth of his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dhets:</hi> to imagine, that, <hi>the eternal Son of God</hi> took <hi>a Body</hi> and <hi>Fleſh,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, merrily contemned and crucified, and that he will not bring the ſame body to receive it's promiſed glory, (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.13.15.) this is neither ſit for the Miſtery of God, nor the admirable contriveance ond diſcovery of his Grace in the Goſpel. For <hi>he muſt reign,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24.28.</note> ſaith our Apoſtle, <hi>till he hath put all his Enemies under his feet;</hi> and till that be done (which as the ſame Apoſtle o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er (<hi>Heb.</hi> 3.8.) we ſee not as yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed) <hi>the end ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>othe i.</hi> the end of the World, and the final judgement. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19.23.</note> not only the <hi>Saints</hi> and the <hi>whole creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> long for, as hoping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en to be <hi>delivered from the bondage of corruption,</hi> (becauſe the <hi>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſhall be taken away <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.11.) but likewiſe ous Saviour ſaid, in Heaven to <hi>exſpect it (Heb.</hi> 10.13.) that ſo he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101343:10"/> may be put into actual poſſeſſion of his ſoveraignty, promiſed, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.) and <hi>have all his Enemies become his footſtool (Pſal.</hi> 110.) After the period of which reign, the humane Nature of <hi>Chriſt</hi> it ſelf ſhall be brought into a ſtate of inferiority and ſubjection unto the Father, <hi>that God may be all in all</hi> (1 Cor. 15, 28.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 6.</note>Laſtly, This was the general and fixed beleif of all the holy men, both before and ſince our Saviours coming, until the time of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy</hi> under <hi>Anti-Chriſt:</hi> what the expectation of the <hi>Prophets</hi> was, ſufficiently appears from the concent and harmony of their predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, upon which the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> (for at that time it is ſaid that <hi>he prophecied Luk</hi> 1.67.) doth make a breif and plain comment (<hi>Luke</hi> 1.68.75.) where he ſaith that now in ſending of Chriſt, God had done what <hi>he had promiſed by the mouth of his holy Prophets, which have been ſince the world began, that we (i.</hi> we <hi>Jewes,</hi> for of them he ſpeaks eſpecially, as alſo doe the Prophets) <hi>ſhould be ſaved from our Enemies,</hi> and from <hi>the hands of all that hate us;</hi> with more words concerning the <hi>Peace: Plenty</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> which was to be in the time of <hi>Chraſt;</hi> as is more fully prophecied of [<hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. <hi>Is.</hi> 11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 34 and 37. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] which time having never yet been in the world, it is infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly certain that it will be, and ought to be expected: what was the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> I have already mentioned out of their writings, and agreeably to what they ſay in expreſs words, was the <hi>beleif</hi> of almoſt almoſt all the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> for above three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years after our Saviour. Thus <hi>papias</hi> [whom <hi>Euſebius</hi> in one part of of his Hiſtory, calls <hi>a learned and eloquent man,</hi> and who ſaith of himſelf that he was <hi>an hearer of</hi> John <hi>the Evangeliſt</hi>] writes poſitively that, <hi>After the firſt reſurrection, the kingdome of Chriſt ſhall endure upon earth a thouſand years,</hi> ſo <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> in that excellent and [by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the writings of our learned and judicious Mr. <hi>Meed</hi>] well known dialogue with <hi>Trypho</hi> the <hi>Jew, as many</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as an Orthadox,</hi> [ſo far was the Church then from judging it an Hereſy] <hi>do expect a Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the hody, which is called the firſt reſurrection, and that the Saints thus raiſed, ſhall live a thouſand years in Jeruſalem, then repaired and beautified:</hi> to the ſame purpoſe <hi>Irenaeus</hi> who wrote about fifty pears after <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> and <hi>Lactantius</hi> aſſerts poſitively that <hi>at the end of the</hi> 6000th <hi>year of the world, righteouſneſs ſhall reign a</hi> 1000 <hi>years, then ſhall Chriſt obtaine the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the whole earth, and there ſhall be, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, which the heathen Poets on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dreamed of, a golden age: Tertullian</hi> doth not only aſſert, but thus argues the caſe in his diſcourſe againſt <hi>Marcion; did alſo confeſs there is a kingdom promiſed to us upon canth, but before heaven, but in another ſtate, namely after
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101343:10"/> the reſurrection for a</hi> 1000 <hi>years in Jeruſalem, a city of divine workmanſhip let down from heaven; which alſo the Apoſtle calls our mother that is above, which alſo the Appoſtle calls, our Mother that is above, and when he affirms that our</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>or, Burgeſs-ſhip, is in Heaven, he doth undoubtedly make it have relation to ſome Heavenly City. This alſo</hi> Ezekiel <hi>knew, and the Apoſtle</hi> Iohn <hi>ſaw, and it was verified lately in the Eaſtern expedition; for it is evident that Heathens alſo being witneſſes that in</hi> Judea; <hi>for</hi> 40 <hi>days together, every Morning, a City did hang down from Heaven, which, as the day grew bright, did vaniſh away with its whole ſtructure; this we ſay, is provided to receive the Saints at the Reſurrection, and to cheriſh them with plenty of all ſpiritual good things, for a recompence of what in this World we have either deſpiſed or loſt, For it is juſt and worthy of God, that his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſhould reign there, where they have been afflicted for his Name, This is the account of the Heavenly Kingdom, after a thouſand years of which (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in which time is included the reſurrection of the Saints, according to the merits of thoſe, who are to rise, ſome ſooner and ſome later) then ſhall be the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the World; and when the judgement of burning is finiſhed, we ſhall be changed in a moment into an Angelical ſubſtance, and ſhalt be tranſlated into an Heavenly Kingdom,</hi> Thus far <hi>Tertulliun,</hi> with whoſe words, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the ſum of what all the Antients have ſaid, I ſhall conclude my Reaſons for proof of the firſt obſervation.</p>
            <p>Before I proceed to the ſecond Obſervation, I will a little inquire, what might be the Reaſon, that a Doctrine ſo plain and evident in Scripture, and ſo fully aſſented to and believed on, in the eldeſt and pureſt times of the Church, came afterwards to be ſo much ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt and decryed; in ſatiſfaction and anſwer to which Query, though much might be ſaid, yet I ſhall content my ſelf with theſe few things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. One Reaſon might be, from that care which in the primitive times, many good men had to avoid any partaking with the error of <hi>Cerinthus, and other groſs and ſenſual Hereticks, who taught that the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years Reign of the Saints on earth, ſhould be ſpent in all manner of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual delight and carnal pleaſures:</hi> Which opinion, being ſo monſtrous in it ſrlf; ſo contrary to the purity of the Goſpvl, and to the very end of our Saviours coming; which was to bring in <hi>true Righteouſneſs and Holineſs (Luke</hi> 1.75.) Many zealous and well meaning men thought they could never ſufficiently ſhow their Abhorrence of ſuch an impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conceit; and therefore, as it is uſual in the heat of oppoſition, they rather choſe to deny even the truth it ſelf, then to imbrace it, as it was clogged and ſullyed with ſuch impure and vitious mixtures: For <hi>Dyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſius,</hi> the moſt learned of all thoſe, who in elder days did oppoſe this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101343:11"/> Doctrine proceeded in his heat and earneſtneſs, as poſitively to deny that the <hi>Revelation of John,</hi> was written by the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> although the Author himſelf doth expreſly affirm it (<hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1.2.) and others after him did deny the whole Book to be <hi>Canonical and inſpired Scripture</hi> whereby they endeavoured to rob the Church of as divine and holy a writing, and of as much tendency, to ſupport the Saints under their ſufferings that both <hi>Heatheniſt and Antichriſtian</hi> men were to bring upon them, as any in the whole Book of God whatever: Unto ſuch deſperate and fearful ſhifts were they heretofore driven, who denyed the Viſible Kingdom of Chriſt upon Earth, and therein wholy eluded the perſpicuity and evidence of that admirable and ſoul refreſhing Prophecy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another cauſe of the oppoſition made againſt this Doctrine, might be the reputation which the learned <hi>Hierome</hi> gained, who being a man very expert or indeed, rather, excellent, in his Interpretation of Scripture, did by reaſon of that prepoſſeſſion and prejudice, which the errors of ſome had occaſioned, ſet himſelf with a great deal of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemence to cenſure this opinion and his authority did eaſily prevail upon the careleſſneſs and credulity of others, who were content to take his word without ever making any farther enquiry into the truth themſelves: Yet even that learned Author himſelf, in his comment, upon the 37th of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> is forced to acknowledge that that prophecy was not yet fulfilled, and he confeſſeth that not only rhe Jews, but likewiſe many Chriſtian writers, as <hi>Victorinus, Severus, Tertullian, Lactantius;</hi> who wrote in <hi>Latine,</hi> and <hi>Iraeneus, Apollinaris, Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> who wrote in Greek, together with many others even in his time, did all expect that that prophecy was to be fulfilled in the <hi>thouſand years Reign,</hi> of which upon that Chapter <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpeaks very favourably, and ſays <hi>it was an opinion not to be reproved:</hi> Yet he continuing to write againſt it; and the Ages following having the countenance of ſo learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a man, embraced haſtily thoſe miſtical expoſitions he gave, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further examining them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Reaſon, why the Scriptures concerning the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> were ſo litle underſtood in the former ages of the Church, might be the uſurpation and ſetting up the <hi>Viſible Kingdom and temporall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy of Antichriſt,</hi> who, as ſoon as ever he was advanced into and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured in his Throne, did preſently apply to himſelf and to his Church, all thoſe Prophecies, which any way concerned the temporal Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Glory of Chriſt and his people: When <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt Chriſtian Emperour, had abſolutely defeated all the force and power
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101343:11"/> of the Heathen Magiſtrates, and made a publick Edict to deſtroy the worſhiy of all <hi>Falſe Gods,</hi> and their <hi>Temples,</hi> then, as many under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it was fulfilled that joyful acclamation, <hi>now is the Salvation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.10.</note> 
               <hi>and the Power, and the Kingdome of our God, and the Authority of his Chriſt;</hi> and in part it might truly be ſaid to have been ſo, for wherever the true Religon is ſet up, and the profeſſors of it encouraged, there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>God reigns,</hi> as he did in <hi>Judea</hi> in the time of <hi>David;</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> making mention of the <hi>glorious Churches</hi> that were then founded, the <hi>great revenues</hi> that were ſetled the ſingular honour that was given to the <hi>Biſhops and Miniſters of the Goſpel</hi> by <hi>Conſtantine, we did,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in this ſee an Embleme of the Reign of Christ:</hi> but this peace and ſecurity purchaſed by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> degenerated preſently into a love of eaſe aand worldly proſperity, which made the Chriſtians generally care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of looking after a better ſtate, to be injoyed in the <hi>firſt reſurrection;</hi> which ſloath and remiſneis of theirs gave advantage to the <hi>Biſhop of Rome,</hi> to wreſt the Dominion out of the <hi>Emperours</hi> hands, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to challenge unto himſelf the exerciſe of their Royalty; he boaſting himſelf to be <hi>the Vicar of Chriſt,</hi> and the perſon appointed to bear rule in his ſtead; the greatneſs of whoſe Dominion all records bear witneſs to, that it did fully anſwer the extent of that Prophecy, wherein it is ſaid, <hi>that the World wondered after the Beaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>and all the Inhabitants of the earth, except a few whoſe names were written in the book of life, did worſhip him,</hi> during whoſe <hi>Univerſal</hi> Reign and Tyranny (for I am content to allow ſuch an <hi>Univerſality</hi> to the Beaſt of <hi>Rome</hi>) it is no wonder if the <hi>true kingdome of Chriſt</hi> was not ſo much as thought of; as when Theives have taken poſſeſſion and by force keep the houſe it is no wonder if the Friends and Neighbors forbear to put in any claim for the right Heir.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, When the <hi>Anti-chriſtian yoke</hi> was, by the gracious working of the power and mercy of God in very weak and contemptible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, thrown off in many Countries and ſcripture light (which before was forcibly deteined and impriſoned in darkneſs) began to recover its luſter, then amongſt the Primitive truths, this doctrine of the <hi>kingdome of Chriſt</hi> did in many places revive, and was by ſeveral learned men at the very firſt reformation aſſerted: but by the ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous attempts of ſome miſtaken men, and the horrid practiſes of thoſe in <hi>Munſter,</hi> this opinion became generally Nauſeous to the moſt ſober and learned of our antient <hi>Proteſtant</hi> writers, and particularly to the judicious and truly worthy Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> whoſe deſerved eſteem in the Church of Chriſt, hath prevailed to keep this great Scripture
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101343:12"/> truth from being ſo much as inquired into; but with due ſubmiſſion and reverence to the memory of ſo many famous men, I do conceive that in this particular they were ſwayed too much by their prejudices, and notwithſtanding their authority, we ought to make for our ſelves a more ſevere and impartial enquiry, for every truth is of a divine original; and ought no more to be denyed, then the Scriptures from whence it is taken, ſuppreſſed, becauſe <hi>unlearned and unſtable men do wreſt it both to their own and to others deſtruction.</hi> It was indeed a great Error, to ſay no more, of thoſe miſtaken (though I hope, as to many of them, well meaning men, who thought themſelves cal; ed to fight up <hi>Chriſt</hi> into his <hi>Throne;</hi> for his <hi>Kingdome</hi> is yet in <hi>Patience (Rev</hi> 1.9.) and will not be fully (over all the world) in power, till he himſelf doth come from Heaven to eſtabliſh it; for he is then <hi>to aboliſh every Authority and Dominion</hi> beſides his own (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24.) That <hi>ſtone</hi> which <hi>Nebuchadnezer</hi> ſaw in his Viſion, to become a <hi>Mountain</hi> and to daſh in peices all former powers; is the Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, and not his <hi>Saints</hi> (as ſome ſuppoſe) for it is he, <hi>who was cut out without hands [Dan.</hi> 2.44.45.] and in the Prophets is often ſtiled <hi>a ſtone,</hi> becauſe of thoſe <hi>ſaving</hi> and <hi>ruining</hi> effects, which follow upon thoſe who receive or refuſe him [compare <hi>Iſ.</hi> 28.12. with <hi>Iſ.</hi> 8.13.14. <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.9.] As at the building of the Temple, it was not <hi>by might or power,</hi> that ſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult a work was effected, but <hi>by the ſpirit of the Lord,</hi> ſo will it be when our Lord erects his <hi>kingdome, he alone ſhall be exalted in that day:</hi> the <hi>ſighes</hi> and <hi>groans</hi> of his oppreſſed people ſhall call him down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and in compaſſion, not of his <hi>perſecuting and ſmiting,</hi> but of his <hi>perſecuted</hi> and <hi>ſuffering</hi> ſervants, he will come and ſave them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their Enemies for them [<hi>Iſ.</hi> 35.4.] They which teach other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>do erre, not knowing the Seriptures:</hi> whoſe miſtakes howevever ought not to have been looked upon to be of ſo dangerous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious a Nature, as that for them the truth it ſelf ſhould be rejected, which is not at all guilty of thoſe conſequences which raſh men do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warily ſtrive to draw from it: and ſo much for the firſt Obſervation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Obſervation was this, <hi>When the Lord Chriſt ſhall come <note place="margin" type="runSum">Ob. 2.</note>from Heaven, to ſet up his kingdom upon earth, all his Saints ſhall come with him:</hi> whereby <hi>Saints</hi> may be meant either <hi>Angels</hi> [as <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.27. and 24 30, 31.] who are called <hi>the Angels of his ſtrength</hi> [2 <hi>Theſ</hi> 1.7.] and <hi>the mighty ones,</hi> who are to deſcend with him, as the executioners of his vengeance againſt all ungodly men, according to <hi>Exoch s</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy <hi>Jude</hi> v. 14.15.] but I doe not take the <hi>Angels</hi> to be principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meant in this place; for hereafter their office will be rather to <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101343:12"/> as they are deſcribed, ſtanding like an out Guard about the <hi>Elders</hi> and the <hi>living Creatures (Rev.</hi> 5.11. and 7.11) Whereas the Prophet <hi>Zachary,</hi> ſpeaks of thoſe <hi>Saints,</hi> that were to <hi>Reign with Chriſt,</hi> and to ſhare with him in his Soveraignty, And therefore by <hi>Saints</hi> here I underſtand <hi>Holy Men,</hi> who lived before this t me, and died in the Faith of Chriſt, of whom the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is to be underſtood (1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.13. and 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10) and deſcribing of the order of the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Choiſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhall riſe the firſt fruits, then they that are Christs, at his coming,</hi> where by <hi>coming,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22.25. <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</hi>
               </note> that the Apoſtle means his <hi>coming to reign,</hi> (which he calls his <hi>appearance and Kingdom</hi> (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.) is plain from that which follows, <hi>then is the end, when he ſhall deliver up the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom unto the Father, when he ſhall have aboliſhed all Dominion, and all au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorety, and power: For he muſt reign till all his Enemies be put under his Feet</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.23.25.) From which words it appears clearly. 1. That when <hi>Chriſt comes, thoſe that are his.</hi> i. e. <hi>Saints,</hi> or <hi>Believers, ſhall come with him.</hi> 2. That between this <hi>coming of Christ,</hi> and <hi>the end,</hi> i. e. the final deſtruction of the World, and conſumation of all things, there ſhall be interpoſed the <hi>reign of Chriſt,</hi> the duration and term of which, though it is not their expreſſed, yet in that viſion, which John after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſaw, we find it is to laſt a <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> all which time the <hi>Saints ſhall reign on earth with Chriſt,</hi> as is particularly and expreſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and the matter <hi>Twice</hi> repeated, to make it more ſure, [<hi>Rev.</hi> 20 4.6.] With that place to the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> agrees what the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle writes to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> [1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 4.14.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14. <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</hi>
               </note>] <hi>If we believe that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus died and roſe again, even ſo them alſo which ſteep in Jeſus, will he bring with him; and [v.</hi> 16.] <hi>The dead in Chriſt, ſhall riſe firſt: Then [i. e. after the reſurrection and reign]</hi> ſhall be what follows concerning the final Judgement, for the <hi>change of Believers that remain alive till the coming of Chriſt</hi> [which is mentioned both there and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51.] ſhall not be done at this <hi>firſt Appearance</hi> of our Saviour, which we are now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing of, for then the Saints, at that time on Earth, ſhall live and reign too, as is plain [<hi>Deu.</hi> 7.18.22 27.] But after this Reign is fully finiſhed and the laſt Judgement begins to be celebrated, then ſhall thoſe Saints that then alive, <hi>be caught up in the Air, and bo for ever with the Lord.</hi> The want of diſtinguiſhing theſe two Times, [which yet is plainly implyed in the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Then,</hi> or, afterward which doth not always ſignifie, what ſhall immediately follow no more then the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>preſently,</hi> or immediately, Mat. 24.29. But only notes the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſucceſs on in the ſeveral event, though at great diſtance of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101343:13"/> times, neglect of obſerving this, hath been none of the leaſt Reaſons, why this place of the Apoſtle, hath been ſo much urged againſt the <hi>reign of the Saints</hi> before the <hi>laſt Judgement,</hi> though indeed rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it doth neceſſarily imply it as containing the very ſame ſenſe with that other paſſage in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> which is not capable of any other interpretation.</p>
            <p>To clear up this a little farther, I deſire that place may be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.23. <hi>The Sun ſhall be aſhamed, and the Moon confounded,</hi> (i. either their light and ſplendour ſhall be nothing in compariſon of that greater Glory, as <hi>Iſa</hi> 60.19. or elſe it ſeems to note that general ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and overthrow of all things, which ſhall immediately preceed (as <hi>Mat,</hi> 24.29.30) <hi>When the Lord of Hoſts ſhall reign in Mount Sion, and in Jeruſalem before his an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ients, (or Elder) in Glory.</hi> Where by <hi>Antients</hi> (in Greek, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> i. e. <hi>elders</hi>) I cannot underſtand any other, then thoſe Elders mentioned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9.10. Who in their Song of Praiſe to the <hi>Lamb, thou waſt ſlain, ſay they, and haſt redeemed us unto God by thy Blood, out of every kindred, and tongue, and people, and Nation, and haſt made us unto our God Kings and Prieſts, ann we ſhall reign upon earth:</hi> Which being ſpoken by the whole Church, under the name of <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Living Creatures,</hi> conſiſting of Officers and Members, it evidently ſhows that ſuch a time will be; according to our Saviours promiſe [<hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26.27. And then all, who have now a <hi>right of Title,</hi> by their Faith in Chriſt, to be Kings and Prieſts, (as is expreſſed <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5.6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5; 9.) ſhall then have <hi>reality of poſſeſſion,</hi> and behold their <hi>King in his beauty, (Iſa.</hi> 33.17.) not at a diſtance, but as a people nigh unto him, and ſitting with him upon his Throne; i. e. Viſibly ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in his Dominion and Glory; which ſtate is fully ſpoke to in <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. compared with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. compared with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. and 61.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons, why Chriſt at his coming, will bring all his <hi>Deceaſed Saints</hi> to live and Reign with him, are.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſ. 1.</note>Firſt, Becauſe of that near Relation, that is between <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Saints;</hi> He is their Head, their Husband. And therefore he thinks not his own Glory compleat without them: As in the Body natural, every Member ſhares in the dignities or indignities done to the Head (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.26.27.) So it is in the body Miſtical of Chriſt; the <hi>Church which is his Body,</hi> is ſaid to be his <hi>fulneſs,</hi> or <hi>complement (Eph.</hi> 1.22.23.) i. e. That which makes him to be a compleat <hi>Head,</hi> which without his <hi>Church, his Body,</hi> he could not be. Hence is that Solicitous and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101343:13"/> care, which our Lord ſhews towards his <hi>ſuffering Saints,</hi> while they live upon Earth, <hi>In all their affliction he is afflicted (Iſa.</hi> 63 9.) which made him (as one that is ſenſibly wounded cryes out for eaſe) to call aloud from Heaven, and to rebuke <hi>Paul,</hi> for <hi>perſecuting</hi> him (<hi>Act.</hi> 9 4 5.) This care, our Saviour will be ſo far from putting off that rather it will be more fully manifeſted, when he comes in his Glory; which is the time, not only of our Lord Chriſts, but of all his Saints and Followers, <hi>Revelation,</hi> as their <hi>Reign on Earth</hi> is ſtiled <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19) For, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>when Chriſt, who is our life, ſhall appear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>then ſhall we alſo appear</hi> (or, <hi>be made manifeſt) with him in Glory (Col.</hi> 3.4.) And to this purpoſe may be applyed that excellent conſolatory pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.19.) <hi>Thy dead men ſhall live, my dead Carkaſs,</hi> (for ſo the Hebrew word ſhould be rendred) <hi>they ſhall ariſe, awake and ſing ye that dwell in the duſt, for thy Dew is the Dew of Herbs, and the Land of the Gyants,</hi> (i. e. of all the great and Mighty in the Earth) <hi>thou ſhalt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</hi> 1. Thou ſhalt utterly ſubdue all thy enemies,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> how great and mighty ſoever. According to that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>The righteous ſhall have dominion over them in the Morning</hi> (or, <hi>in that Morning</hi>) namely that; of the <hi>firſt Reſurrection,</hi> For then, <hi>they ſhall tread down the wicked, and they ſhall be as Aſhes under the ſoles of their Feet. [Mal.</hi> 4.3.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.14.</note>] And that becauſe of their near Relation unto Chriſt, who hath loved them and conveyed this power to them [<hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26.27.]</p>
            <p>Secondly, Another reaſon, why Chriſt will bring his deceaſed<note place="margin" type="runSum">R. 2.</note> Saints to Reign with him, may be taken from that proportion which God obſerves in the diſtribution of rewards unto his people: For though the <hi>reward</hi> it ſelf in general <hi>is of grace,</hi> yet God is pleaſed to obſerve this order and method in the diſpenſing it; that it ſhould be ſome way anſwerable unto his peoples ſufferings and actings for him: Thus the Apoſtle [2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.11.12.] <hi>This is a faithful ſaying; If we ſuffer with Chriſt, we ſhall alſo reign with him:</hi> And as I have already urged the words of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> ſo doth the Apoſtle argue, in his ſecond E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> [2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.4.7.] after he had ſaid that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions and tribulations, which the Chriſtians then indured, were permitted to be laid upon them by God, that <hi>they might be counted worthy of the kingdom of God for which they ſuffered;</hi> He gives this as a Reaſon, <hi>Becauſe it is a righteous thing with God to recompenſe Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto them that trouble you, but unto you that are troubled reſt, with us when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven with his mighty Angels.</hi> He that ſerves <hi>Chriſt</hi> and follows the <hi>Lamb</hi> here, ſhall hereafter be in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101343:14"/> the ſame place and partake of the ſame honour with him (<hi>Joh.</hi> 12.26.) And thus our Saviour prayed for them, <hi>Father, whom thou hast given me,</hi> I <hi>will that where</hi> I <hi>am, they alſo may be with me, that they may behold my glory which thou haſt given me (Joh.</hi> 17 24) part of which glory is that the Father,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> by an Eternal Decree hath ſet (or, as the Hebrew word ſignifies, <hi>Anointed] his Son upon his holy hill of Sion;</hi> And when he returns from Heaven to take poſſeſſion of that Soveraignty which the Father long ſince promiſed him, his faithful followers <hi>ſhall enter into his Joy</hi> i. e. As our Saviour him ſelf explains that Phraſe (<hi>Luk.</hi> 19.17) <hi>they ſhall have command and ſhare the Dominion with him:</hi> Therefore <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are ſaid to be heirs of God, and Co-heirs with Chriſt (Rom.</hi> 8.17.] and <hi>Partners with Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>Partakers of Chriſt, [Heb.</hi> 3.14.] i. e. as <hi>Peter</hi> expreſſeth, <hi>Partakers of the glory which ſhall be revealed</hi> (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1) which <hi>glory</hi> is, as to the beginning of it, that which I have already mentioned, and our Saviour hath fully declared, when he ſaith, that, <hi>In the regeneration they ſhall ſit with him upon Thrones to rule and judge [Mat.</hi> 19.28.]</p>
            <p>The ſum therefore of this ſecond obſervation is briefly contained in theſe three propoſitions which are all evident and clear in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. With Chriſt all the <hi>deceaſed Saints,</hi> both <hi>Patriarch, Prophets, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> ſhall be raiſed up and be brought to the Earth, to ſee and ſhare in the Royalty of his Government (<hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Saints at that time living upon Earth both Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, but eſpecially the Jews (unto whom the <hi>firſt domion,</hi> and chief <hi>Soveraignty</hi> is frequently promiſed as <hi>Iſa</hi> 49.23. and 7 60.11.12. <hi>M ch.</hi> 4.8. ſhall injoy all that time, the greateſt ſecurity, peace and proſperity immaginable doing all the actions of a mortal life, but without either ſin or ſorrow <hi>for they ſhall be all righteous (Iſa.</hi> 60.21.) And the Lord will then put his Spirit into them, without ever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing it any more (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 39 29.) and <hi>Sathan</hi> ſhall be chained up and hindred from deceiving, during the whole Term of a 1000 years (Zech. 13.2. Rev. 20 2, 4, 6.)</p>
            <p n="3">3. After this ſtate of things and the 1000 years is expired, then follows the Inſurrection of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> and the final judgement as is expreſſed (<hi>Rev.</hi> 20.7.) And then ſhall the Saints, that remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that time, be changed, and death for ever ſwallowed up in victory and <hi>the Reign of Chriſt and of his</hi> Saints, hitherto managed upon earth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101343:14"/> be tranſlated into and conſumated in Heaven, <hi>that God may be all in all</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28.)</p>
            <p>If any ask, as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> did our Saviour when he had diſcourſed to him concerning the great <hi>miſtery of Regeneration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>how can theſe things be</hi> I may reply, in our Saviours words. <hi>art thou a Maſter or Teacher, in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, and knoweſt not theſe things?</hi> For as the Apoſtle ſpeaks,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.</note> handling partly this very Doctrine <hi>Whereas ws ought to be teachers for the time,</hi> conſidering how long the Light of the Goſpel hath ſhone among us, <hi>we have ſtill need of Milk,</hi> ſitting down ſatisfied with the <hi>loweſt Elements and Beginnings of Chriſtianity,</hi> ſuch are the Doctrines of Faith in Chriſt and repentance towards God, which the Apoſtle calls the word of the beginning of Chriſt (<hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1.) But we cannot bear <hi>ſtrong meat,</hi> nor are careful to <hi>be carried unto Perfection:</hi> i. e. unto the height and perfection of our Hope and Holy Profeſſion, to the full compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, belief, and avowed owning of which we ought to arrive, and leave the ſolution of all doubts and ſcruples, unto the power of God which is able to the full to effect whatever he hath promiſed when the <hi>Angel</hi> had told <hi>Mary</hi> that the ſame Perſon who was the <hi>Eternal Son of God,</hi> ſhould become Man, and be conceived in her Womb ſhe asked preſently! <hi>How ſhall this be?</hi> But after he had farther revealed that, <hi>the holy Spirit ſhould come upon her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>and the power of the moſt High overſhadow her,</hi> by whoſe ſecret and inconceivable acting that great and ſtupendious miſtery, ſhould be effected, we do not find then that ſhe queſtioned or doubted any more, but in an humble reſignation of her ſeif gave immediately thanks to God, <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>the Handmaid of the Lord, let it be unto me according to thy word;</hi> The ſame ſhould every true believer do in this caſe, for this <hi>Temporal glory of Chriſt and of his Saints:</hi> is not only promiſed: in every whit as expreſs words but likewiſe mention is made of the ſame <hi>creating</hi> and <hi>Almighty power,</hi> as ingaged to perform it, and therefore God ſpeaking of this very ſtate, commands his people <hi>not to remember former things, (Iſa.</hi> 43.18, 19:) Becauſe he was doing a <hi>new thing,</hi> in compariſon of which all former acts of power and mercy, exepted by God on the behalf of his people ſhould be obſcured and darkned, as ſtars are by the brighter glory of the Sun, ſo (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17.) <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith God I <hi>am creating a new Heaven, and a new Earth, In which as Peter</hi> hath it (2 Pet 3.13.) <hi>Righteouſneſs is to dwell; and which we expect according to his Promiſe,</hi> and this is that time of our Saviours, and of his Saints <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101343:15"/> Kingdom,</hi> which will bring a Reformation upon the whole World and when it once doth take place, <hi>former things ſhall no more be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, nor come into mind:</hi> In that place of <hi>Iſay,</hi> the word <hi>creating</hi> is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remarkable, for when the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> foretold the Birth of Chriſt: he uſeth the ſame expreſſions (<hi>Jer.</hi> 31.22.) <hi>Behold the Lord createth a new thing, a woman ſhall compaſs a Man.</hi> i. e. In other words, <hi>a Virgin ſhall conceive a Son Iſa.</hi> 7.14.) which thing when it was done was ſo <hi>new,</hi> that is, ſo ſtrange and extraordinary, that the Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi> who foretold it, complains, <hi>Who hath believed our report, (Iſa.</hi> 53.1.) and yet the exact and punctual fulfilling of that, which is far greater and leſs intelligible, will not prevail with us to believe the other, but when our Lord ſhall come, <hi>he will ſcarcely,</hi> as to this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; <hi>find Faith upon earth (Luke</hi> 18.8.) So little expectation will there be, <hi>of his A pearance and of his Kingdom,</hi> which as they are joined by the Apoſtle, ſo they will be revealed together [2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.] And all who deny this: may receive this anſwer, which our Saviour gave to the <hi>Sadduces, who denyed the Reſurrection, They erre, not knowing the Scriptures</hi> [which have clearly promiſed ſuch a ſtate] <hi>nor the power of God</hi> (which is fully able to effect it.)</p>
            <p>Here I might end, as having fully, [and, as I think, to all unpreju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced perſons, convincingly] proved the Truth of the Doctrine I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to deliver, but becauſe one Argument commonly urged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, is a ſuppoſal, that this Doctrine hath little or no influence upon our preſent Practice, but rather tends to unſettle the World; which was the Outcry raiſed againſt it of old [<hi>Luke</hi> 23 2, 5. and <hi>Acts</hi> 17.6, 7.] Then to build up any in true Holineſs, I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore briefly inſiſt upon a few practical inferences wh ch follow hence, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Uſe 1.</note>Firſt, This Doctrine, concerning the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt upon earth,</hi> ſerves to inform us, what we ſhould continually pray unto God for, and make one of our moſt earneſt and importunate Petitions, namely this. <hi>Thy Kingdom come;</hi> That God, in mercy to his People, and in zeal for his own Glory, would haſten the time of ſetting up this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that ſo the wickedneſs of the wicked [<hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.9.] and the <hi>ſufferings of the righteous,</hi> may come to a full end. For when <hi>God reigns the wicked ſhall be deſtroyed out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s earth (Pſal.</hi> 10.16. comp. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104.35.) and thus as our Saviour himſelf ſpeaks in the Parable, <hi>The Son of Man ſhall ſend his Angels, and they ſhall gather all the ſcandals, and ſuch as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101343:15"/> commit iniquity out of his Kingdom (Mat.</hi> 13.41.) But to bring this to paſs, it muſt be the work of <hi>Fervent prayer,</hi> God the Father did not promiſe to give <hi>the Nations for the inheritance of his ſon,</hi> but upon the condition of his asking it. <hi>ask of me;</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and I will give the Nations for thine Inheritance, (Pſal.</hi> 2 7, 8.) So when God, by the Prophet <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel,</hi> had promiſed the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that he would not only par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don their ſins, but <hi>put his Spirit into them,</hi> and then give them a laſting and peaceable poſſeſſion of their Land, he adds, <hi>yet for this I will be inquired of by the Houſe of Iſrael to do it for them (Ezek.</hi> 36, 37.) For Gods Promiſes, though never ſo abſolute in the letter and expreſſion of them; yet, are ſo far from excluding Prayer, that they are given as <hi>Motives</hi> to quicken us in it; ſince in them God hath graciouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded us ſo many Arguments, by which our Faith may be ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and incouraged to plead with him: Thus our Saviour having fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told <hi>the coming of his Kingdom</hi> [for of that he ſpeaks <hi>Luke</hi> 21.31.] And given ſeveral ſigns, that were to be the Tokens and Fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of its approach, he concludes, <hi>Watch ye therefore and pray always [v.</hi> 36.] For the performance of which duty, beſides the command obliging to it, we have this great incouragement; That the more, the Hearts of Gods people are drawn out, in earneſt expectation of-and vehement longing for, the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> they may be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the nearer it is, Thus the Pſalmiſt, praying that God would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore his people, concludes confidently (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 112 13, 14.) <hi>Thou wil ariſe, thou wilt have mercy upon Zion,</hi> for the time to favour her, <hi>yea the ſet time</hi> of which God had ſpoken (<hi>Iſa,</hi> 60.22) I <hi>the Lord will haſten it in its time is come.</hi> Of which peremptory aſſertion he gives this Reaſon, <hi>For thy people take pleaſure in her stones; and they favour the duſt, thereof.</hi> As if he had ſaid the deſires of thy people are now more then ordinarily raiſed up and carried out, in hope of a ſudden re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration, notwithſtanding the preſent viſible difficulties, which may hinder ſuch an expectation by ſeeing the Rubbiſh and Ruines of <hi>Sion,</hi> and therefore I conclude, that the time of her deliverance is nigh: For this we muſt take for granted, that a <hi>Spirit of Prayer,</hi> which is the <hi>Spirit of God in Believers (Rom.</hi> 8 14.26, 27.) is never given out but there is a willingneſs and propenſity in the Heart of God at that time to grant the very thing, which he is prayed to for, Thus the Pſalmiſt (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17.) joyns together <hi>Gods preparing the Heart</hi> of his People, and the <hi>inclining of his own ear to hear,</hi> Thus it was, in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101343:16"/> 
               <hi>Church of the Jews,</hi> at our Saviours firſt coming; there was then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a general expectation raiſed of him, <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> is ſaid to be one of thoſe that waited for the <hi>Kingdom of God, (Mark.</hi> 15 43.) <hi>Simeon, Anna,</hi> and many others, <hi>did look for the conſolation and redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Iſrael,</hi> as the coming of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> is called (<hi>Luke</hi> 2 25, 28.) And not only they, but even the generality of the Jews were then <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting that Chriſt ſhould come (Luke</hi> 3.15.) And as they expected and believed, ſo it was indeed though the mean appearance which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour then manifeſted himſelf in kept the greateſt part of them, from believing in him. What the Church of God did, at our Saviours firſt we ſhould think it our duty, to do in reference to his <hi>Second coming,</hi> namely, <hi>Be expecting and haſtning it</hi> (as <hi>Peters</hi> expreſſion is) 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12. i. e. By heads lifted up,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> be looking intently for it, and by arms ſtretched out in Prayer, be earneſtly requeſting it: For if the <hi>Virgins ſlumber,</hi> it is no wonder if the <hi>Bridegroom tarries</hi> And if his people do not deſire him to haſten, how can we expect but <hi>our Lord will delay his coming?</hi> This therefore we ſhould, with all manner of religious importunity, inceſſanly beg for, and offer a kind of <hi>Holy violence</hi> to God, <hi>giving him do reſt,</hi> (as the expreſſion is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.1, 6, 7) Till he doth eſtabliſh his word, and ſend us our Promiſed <hi>Lord and King</hi> from Heaven, that we may be <hi>Kings and Prieſts</hi> with him, and ſhare in all his Royal Glories.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Uſe 2.</note>Secondly, we may learn from hence, as to <hi>pray,</hi> ſo to <hi>wait with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience for our Lords coming,</hi> For he hath onely withdrawn his reſidence from earth for a time, till all things be made fit for his return, and then he will not delay, when a few changes more are paſt, he will come from Heaven, and by bringing in <hi>everlaſting righteouſneſs,</hi> the effect of which is ſtability, and <hi>peace,</hi> he will put a full end to all fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Mutation. We ſhould therefore as our Saviour adviſed his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.19. <hi>In patience poſſeſs our ſouls;</hi> that is as <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks <hi>Let patience have its perfect work</hi> in us (Jam. 1.4.) <hi>that we may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and intire, wanting nothing,</hi> or <hi>in nothing, a little patience and for a</hi> little time, will not ſerve our turn; for <hi>Chriſtian patience</hi> hath no bound to it but is to be terminated only in the <hi>coming</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the exhortation runs; <hi>Be ye patient, Brethren unto the com ng of our Lord (Jam.</hi> 5.7, 8.) This grace is requiſite in all the actions which we do as Chriſtians, in <hi>Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing,</hi> to retain the <hi>Seed,</hi> and to br ng forth anſwerable <hi>Fruit,</hi> which is brought forth with patience (<hi>Luke</hi> 8.15.)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101343:16"/> In <hi>Praying,</hi> that we be not dicouraged, and for want of a preſent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, be tempted to give it over <hi>Luke</hi> 18 1. In <hi>ſufferings,</hi> that <hi>we faint not,</hi> but reſolutely hold out our <hi>Race, (Heb.</hi> 12.1.) And therefore the Goſpel, which ſo much enjoyns and requires it, is called the <hi>Word of Chriſts patience, (Rev.</hi> 3.10.) But in nothing is <hi>patience</hi> more neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, then <hi>in watching for our Lords appearance,</hi> and therefore, with <hi>the work of Faith,</hi> and <hi>labour of Love;</hi> is joyned, <hi>the patience of the Hope of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> (1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3.) i. e. the patient waiting for and expecting him from Heaven, as it is explained <hi>v.</hi> 10. So (2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.5.) the Apoſtle prays, <hi>that God would direct their hearts unto the Love of God, &amp; patience of Chriſt,</hi> where <hi>patience,</hi> as alſo the Greek word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies <hi>Patient expectation;</hi> for what faith believes, and prayer ſolicites, that <hi>patience</hi> waits for; (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8 24, 25) <hi>Of which ſaith the Apoſtle,</hi> to the believing <hi>Hebrews, ye have need Hab.</hi> 10.36.) For becauſe our Lord (not <hi>delays,</hi> in the ſenſe we uſually take <hi>delay</hi> (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3 9. but forbears his <hi>coming,</hi> till the proper time of it, which is not yet fully come, becauſe that all things that are to preceed it are not yet accompliſhed therefore we had need be armed with patience, or elſe our haſt and impatience may undo us; As that <hi>wicked ſervant,</hi> who relaxed his watch, and fell to <hi>fleſhly pleaſures,</hi> loſt thereby all the benefit of his former vigilance ſo will it alſo fare with us, unleſs <hi>by patient perſeverance,</hi> in well doing, we ſeek for Glory, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Immortality (<hi>Rom</hi> 2.8.) like rubbiſh, by Fire, and a new Theatre or Throne of Glory; erected for men of another Nature and ſpirit to converſe in. How greatly then ſhould we rejoyce to drink of our <hi>Lords Cup,</hi> and to taſte of the ſame ſufferings, ſince for ought we know the <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Martyrdom</hi> of a few more, may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the number, and bring our Lord from Heaven, to avenge their quarrel; and then our Tears will be rewarded, by having them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever wiped away, and each drop of blood that hath been ſhed in this illuſtrious cauſe, will add a Glory and a Wreath unto our Crown: Then ſhall we in the Prophets words, cry out and ſay, <hi>Lo this is our God, we have waited for him, and he have ſaved us: This is the Lord, we have waited for him we will be glad and rejoyce in his Salvation</hi> (Iſa. 25.9.) In which place this very Time and Reign is ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we ſhould learn from hence to make a diligent inquiry into<note place="margin" type="runSum">Uſe 3.</note> our <hi>Saintsſhip,</hi> for ſince, when <hi>our Lord come,</hi> none but <hi>his Saints ſhall
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101343:17"/> come with him</hi> we ought to make a careful ſearch, whither we be indeed <hi>Saints</hi> or not, leaſt in that day of Tryal, <hi>which will be revealed with fire,</hi> we be found deceivers of our ſelves, and ſo <hi>be put to ſhame by him at his Appearance,</hi> [1 <hi>John</hi> 2 28] Many Profeſſors like the <hi>fooliſh Virgins,</hi> and thoſe, who boaſted of their <hi>prophecying in the Name of Chriſt, (Mat.</hi> 7.21.23.) will be found miſtaken and inſtead of partaking of <hi>the Reſurrection of the Righteous,</hi> to whom alone the reward is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (<hi>Luke</hi> 14.14.) will be <hi>raized up to ſhame and everlaſting contempt, (Dan.</hi> 12.1. with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66 24) beholding the glory of others, who formerly were much inferiour to themſel es, but ſee themſelves ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded which will increaſe their miſery (<hi>Luke</hi> 13.28, 29.) and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that inward anguiſh, which is expreſſed by <hi>Weeping and Gnaſhing of Teeth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 112.10.</note> Thus the Pſalmiſt, ſpeaking of the happineſs of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>The wicked,</hi> ſaith he <hi>ſhall ſee it, and be grieved, he ſhall gnaſh his Teeth, and melt away;</hi> The <hi>coming of Chriſt,</hi> though it be a time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing, (as it is called <hi>Acts</hi> 3 19.) to his diſtreſſed and perſecuted Servant, yet to others it will be very terrible which makes the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet inquire, <hi>who can abide the day of his coming, or who can ſtand when he apprars? (Mal.</hi> 3.4.) For he will come as <hi>fire to chaff, to burn the wicked out of the earth, (Mal.</hi> 4.1.) And therefore we had need ask, whether we can, <hi>like Gold, indure his refining,</hi> and continue unſcorched in the midſt of ſuch <hi>everlaſting burning, (Iſa.</hi> 33.14) Chriſt comes from Heaven, <hi>to take vengeance on his enemies</hi> (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Jude v.</hi> 14.15.) as well as to be <hi>glorified in his Saints; and admired in them that beleive</hi> (2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7.10.) And therefore we have the <hi>Great and Rich men</hi> of the Earth calling out <hi>to the Rocks to fall upon them, and to the Hills to cover them (Rev.</hi> 6.16.17.) becauſe truth of Holineſs, and nothing elſe will be of any avail at that day, which ſhould make us very ſerious in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining our ſelves about it.</p>
            <p>Among many other <hi>ſigns,</hi> which may be given of our <hi>Saints-ſhip,</hi> I ſhall content my ſelf with mentioning only two, becauſe they do in an eſpecial manner relate to the matter in hand.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Sign 1.</note>Firſt, <hi>What love have we for the Appearance of Chriſt, and how are we affected with the thoughts and hopes of his coming? Abraham</hi> rejoyced in Hope to ſee that day, and when he ſaw it, by an eye of Faith, <hi>he was glad (John</hi> 8.56.) The ſame diſpoſition ſhould be in all Believers,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101343:17"/> who are <hi>the Children of Abraham;</hi> and ſo much the rather, becauſe now <hi>Chriſt is to appear without ſin (i.</hi> e. in his full Beauty, &amp; for luſtre of Majeſty, without any Cloud of imputed ſin to eclipſe; and to hide his <hi>Comelineſs,</hi> as formerly there was, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 53.2.) and this he will do <hi>for ſalvation unto them who expect him, (Heb.</hi> 9.28.) This the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> makes a certain ſign of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> converſion to the Faith, that they did <hi>expect the Revelation of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7.) for he cannot be a true Diſciple of Chriſt, <hi>a child of the Bride-chamber,</hi> who doth not inwardly grieve and mourn for the <hi>abſence of the Bridegroom (Mat</hi> 9.15.) which <hi>Mourning</hi> muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be accompanied with earneſt longing <hi>to ſee one of his dayes (Luke</hi> 17.22.) And therefore the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the great work that was wrought by the ſpirit of God upon the <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> he makes the ſumme and height of it to be this, <hi>They were turned from Idols to ſerve the living and the true God, and to wait for his Son from Heaven</hi> (1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10.) And again, in his Epiſtle to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>The Crown of Righteouſneſs was laid up,</hi> not for himſelf alone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Comp. Tit.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.12.</note> but <hi>for all thoſe that loved our Lords appearance</hi> (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.) So that to have a love for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and a longing earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that <hi>his Name may be glorified,</hi> and <hi>his Kingdom ſet up in the Earth,</hi> it is an undoubted ſign of the truth of Faith, and that the <hi>ſpirit of Chriſt</hi> hath taken poſſeſſion of us; <hi>For the Spirit and Bride ſay, come, and every one that heareth</hi> (or <hi>readeth) let him ſay Come; Yea O come Lord Jeſus, come quickly</hi> (Rev. 22.17, 20.)</p>
            <p>Secondly, What care have we <hi>to walk worthy of Chriſt;</hi> This is<note place="margin" type="runSum">Sign 2.</note> that which the Apoſtle very often earneſtly preſſeth. <hi>We teſtifie,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that you walk worthy of God, who hath called you unto his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Glory</hi> (1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.12.) and having ſaid (2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.14.) <hi>That they were called to the obtaining of the Glory of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> he adds, <hi>therefore ſtand faſt (Ver.</hi> 15.) We are not onely <hi>to be holy as the Lord is holy,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15.16.) but we are to have this end in it, that <hi>when Chriſt appears, we may have confidence</hi> (1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.28.) So alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Peter; Expecting,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>theſe things</hi> (i. e. <hi>New Heaven, and a new Earth, wherein Righteouſneſs,</hi> and the Practicers of it, <hi>is to dwell) give diligence to be found ſpotleſs and blameleſs by him</hi> (2 Pet. 3.13.) which likewiſe upon the ſame grounds, is the exhortation of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> (1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23.)</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:101343:18"/>
            <p>There are <hi>Four things,</hi> which theſe <hi>Expectants</hi> ſhould have an eſpecial care to purifie, and to ſeparate themſelves from.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Fleſhly Luſts,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Worldly Cares,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Falſe Worſhips,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Servile Fears.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, from <hi>Fleſhly Luſts:</hi> What they are I need not mention For, as the Apoſtle obſerves, <hi>The works of the Fleſh are manifeſt (Gal.</hi> 5.19.20.) which whoever do indulge and allow themſelves in, <hi>they cannot inherit the Kingdom of Chriſt and of God</hi> (V. 21. Eph. 5.5.) The <hi>New Jeruſalem which comes down fram Heaven,</hi> and is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but <hi>the Kingdom of Chriſt, and of his Saints upon Earth</hi> is a place of ſo great Purity that <hi>no unclean thing ſhall enter into it</hi> (Rev 21.27 (<hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Swine,</hi> all <hi>Voluptuous</hi> and <hi>hurtfull Beaſts</hi> like them, they are <hi>without</hi> the Gates of that City (Rev. 22.15) A Chriſtian is ſaid to be already <hi>raiſed with Chriſt</hi> (Col. 2.12) and as to the Truth of our Graces, we are to look upon our ſelves, as <hi>Citizens and Inhabitants,</hi> not of Earth, but of <hi>Heaven</hi> (Phil. 3 20.) and ſo to live like thoſe that are acted by an Heavenly <hi>Spirit,</hi> which daily prompts us to look after a better hope then any thing this preſent <hi>Fleſh</hi> affords, <hi>To ſow unto,</hi> i. e. to gratifie which, is onely to take a great deal of pains <hi>that we may Reap Corruption</hi> (Gal. 6.8.] the ſame <hi>Spirit,</hi> which hereafter ſhall <hi>Raiſe</hi> and <hi>Glorifie</hi> our <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Bodies,</hi> muſt now <hi>Sanctifie</hi> them [<hi>Romt</hi> 8.11.] or <hi>elſe we ſhall die [v.</hi> 13.] <hi>i. e.</hi> we ſhall Riſe only to have <hi>our Portion in the Lake</hi> of <hi>Fire, which is the ſecond Death,</hi> where all the <hi>Abominable and Unbelievers</hi> are, [Rev. 21.8.]</p>
            <p>Secondly, From <hi>Worldly Cares:</hi> we are commanded in an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner, <hi>to beware that our hearts be not burdned with the cares of this life</hi> [Rev. 21.34.] For, by ſuch, <hi>the day of the Lords coming</hi> can neither be Foreſeen nor deſired; both their Heart and Eyes being already filled and poſſeſſed with another Object: When we cry out as <hi>Peter</hi> did. <hi>It is good for us to be here,</hi> we ſhall never care to come down from the <hi>Mount,</hi> which we here reared up, and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied to our ſelves. As in the time of publick Judgements, it is our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101343:18"/> Duty <hi>not to ſeek after great things for our ſelves</hi> [Jer. 45.5.] ſo when we are aſſured that <hi>Chriſt,</hi> at his <hi>Appearance and Kingdom,</hi> will deſtroy this preſent frame of things, and cauſe all the beauty of it to periſh; for any ambitiouſly to affect and purſue a preſent fading Greatneſs and Glory, it argues plainly that their Faith is but ſmall, and that they have little or no expectation of ſomething better: Who rightly apprehend, and frequently reflect upon the inevitable <hi>ſhakings</hi> and Convulſions, which the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of this World are ſubject to, will never reſt ſatisfied till they have ſecured unto themſelves a place in that <hi>Kingdom which cannot be ſhaken</hi> [Heb 12.28.] Believers, with <hi>Abraham, David,</hi> and the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> of old, are but <hi>Pilgrims and Strangers</hi> here [1 Pet. 2.11.] and therefore they are daily to be looking for, and up to <hi>that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly City</hi> which is the <hi>New Jeruſalem let down from Heaven, whoſe Maker and Builder is God</hi> [Heb. 11.16.]</p>
            <p>Thirdly, From <hi>Falſe Worſhips; who follow the Lamb,</hi> muſt have <hi>his,</hi> and <hi>his Fathers name upon their Foreheads, and keep themſelves undefiled with VVomen</hi> [Rev. 14.1, 4, 5,] i. e. They muſt openly own the true Worſhip of God, and carefully avoid all Idolatrous Mixtures; ſhunning all manner of Communion with <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterous Churches,</hi> from which who ſo keep themſelves they are <hi>the Virgins</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Revelation:</hi> And this is to be their State during the whole time of the Reign of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to whom [becauſe <hi>they hold the Commands of God, and the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Jeſus</hi>) they are called <hi>Witneſſes</hi> [Rev. 11.] Since we are <hi>Redeemed by Chriſt,</hi> we muſt take heed in every reſpect, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in this, wherein his Fathers honour is ſo much concerned, how we be found the <hi>Servants of Men,</hi> [1 Cor. 7.23]</p>
            <p>When the <hi>ſixth Vial</hi> is poured out, which I take to be the time when the <hi>Jews</hi> (who are called the <hi>Kings from the Eaſt</hi>) ſhall have their way prepared for them over <hi>Euphrates</hi> to return into their own Land, at which time <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf ſhall appear at the Head of them (<hi>Mic.</hi> 2.12.13.) Then is there this voice, as it were from heaven, <hi>Behold, I come as a Thief, bleſſed is he that watcheth, and who keepeth his Garments, that he doth not walk naked Rev.</hi> 16.17.) By <hi>Garments</hi> there, is meant the <hi>righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> for <hi>juſtification,</hi> and that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101343:19"/> way of holineſs for <hi>ſanctification,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath revealed he will be ſerved and obeyed in; Which whoſoever ſhall not at that time be found walking in, but worſhips God, according to his own or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens devices, <hi>his works</hi> (as the Prophet threatned the hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical and ceremonial Jews) <hi>ſhall not prove a covering to him,</hi> but both they, and all the lies which are found out to ſupport them, ſhall be ſwept a way: <hi>the fire,</hi> wherein that day <hi>ſhall be revealed, will burn up all the Droſs and ſtubble,</hi> wherewith vain men think they adorn, but indeed only disfigure or rather defile, Gods worſhip, Whatever Paint may be put upon Men Inventions, it will upon an impartial ſearch be found, almoſt as little a ſin, not to ſerve God at all, as to ſerve him in any other way then be himſelf hath commanded: For the one indeed is bare faced impiety, but the other is thus far like unto it, in that it preſumes to <hi>teach God wiſdom,</hi> and ſo <hi>Judas</hi> like, betrays Gods honour, while it pretends to kiſs him.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, from <hi>Servile Fears:</hi> there is nothing more unworthy of a Chriſtian, then <hi>to be afraid of men:</hi> ſince this tends to the diſhonor of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as if he were not a <hi>great King,</hi> and able to ſave all his <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> This charge he laid upon his Diſciples, when he ſent them to preach, <hi>be not afraid of them which can only kill the body, (Mat.</hi> 10, 28.) and afterwards, when he encouraged the Church of <hi>Smyrna, fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer; the Divil ſhall caſt ſome of you in priſon, that you may be tempted, be thou faithful unto death, and</hi> I <hi>will give thee a Crown of Life, (Rev.</hi> 2.10.) This promiſe we do evidently disbelieve, if we give way ſo far to our Fear, as to be kept from open confeſſing; and therefore the <hi>fearful and unbelieving</hi> are joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as thoſe that are to have their part in the ſame <hi>lake of fire (Rev.</hi> 21.8.) When the Apoſtle preſſeth <hi>Timothy</hi> to be earneſt <hi>in ſtirring up that gift which God had beſtowed upon him</hi> (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.) he uſeth this Argument, For God <hi>hath not given us the Spirit of Fear but of Power,</hi> (v. 7.) And thence he proceeds to exhort him, <hi>be not therefore aſhamed of the teſtimony of our Lord, v.</hi> 8. <hi>but ſuffer affliction with the Goſpel according to the power of God,</hi> all thoſe diſtinctions and evaſions, which men have deviſed to ſhift off the Croſs, will be found at laſt to be only the <hi>hiding places,</hi> that <hi>fear</hi> hath provided to ſhelter
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101343:19"/> it ſelf in, and what the Apoſtle affirmed concerning the <hi>ceremonie</hi> preſſed and contended for in his time, may be aſſerted concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all, that thoſe <hi>who compelled others to them, did it only that they might not be perſecuted by the croſs of Chriſt (Gal.</hi> 6.12.) But ſince the Croſs doth prepare the way for the Crown, let us not <hi>fear,</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pray, as the Apoſtles did, when they were ſilenced by their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, <hi>Now Lord behold their threats and give unto thy ſervants with all boldneſs to ſpeak thy word (Acts</hi> 14.29.) Courage becomes a Chriſtian ſo much, that without it he cannot be one; but will, upon every tryal, expoſe his Lords Honour and Power to contempt and cen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:101343:20"/>
            <head>The Reader is intreated to correct theſe following ERRATAS.</head>
            <p>PAge 1. Line 25. is read it is.</p>
            <p>P. 2. L. 31. acknowledge r. acknowledged.</p>
            <p>P. 5. L. 19. Ocadiah r. Obadiah.</p>
            <p>P. 6. L. 6 Wreſtling r. wreſting ib. L. 28. minute r. minute ib. L. 30. their r. theſe ib. L. 33. conſiderate r. conſiderable.</p>
            <p>P. 7. L. 2. much difficult r. much more difficult ib. L. 18. the reaſon r. this reaſon ib. L. 23. or plea r. of p ea ib. L. 31. ſeeming r. ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ib. L. 37. r. his return ib. L. 39 r in a limited.</p>
            <p>P. 8. L. 4. Seſum r. Telum ib. Chap. r. Cup. ib. L. 30. too r. ſo.</p>
            <p>P. 9. L. 3. raſen r. riſen ib. L. 7. his r. her ib. L 10. deceived r. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed ib. L. 16. an Univerſal r. of ſuch an Univerſal ib. L. 37. exſpect or watch r. expects or waits.</p>
            <p>P. 10. L. 10. Acts r. Arts ib. L. 20 r. intimate.</p>
            <p>P. 11. L. 26. hebrews r. hebrew text ib. l. 29 proves the curioſity r. reproved their curioſity 1. L. required r. inquired.</p>
            <p>P. 12. L. 23. <hi>it duration r. it's duration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 13. l. 30. merrily contemned r meerly to be contemned ib. L. 32. Miſtery r. Majeſty ib. L. 33. ond r. and ib. l. 39, the canſe r. the curſe.</p>
            <p>P. 14. L. 30. an Orthodox r are Orthodox ib. L. 34. r. fifty years ib. L. 37. r. there ſhall be that ib. L. 39. r. We do alſo ib. L. 40. r. upon Earth.</p>
            <p>P. 15. L. 2. dele, which alſo the Apoſtle calls our Mother that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 16. L. 7. that heathens r. the heathen.</p>
            <p>P. 16. L. 12. proceeded r. proceeded ſo far</p>
            <p>P. 17. L. 24. Beaſt or Church.</p>
            <p>P. 39. L. 49 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> r. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>P. 23. L. 33. exepted r. exerted.</p>
            <p>P. 27. L. 27. like Rubbiſh by fire r. When <hi>Gods Jewels are made up</hi> and that <hi>Summe ſealed,</hi> then ſhall this periſhing frame of things (which now have <hi>the holy ſeed</hi> for its hidden ſupport) be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med like Rubbiſh by fire.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101343:20"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
